He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation,
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey greetings, Dragon Slayer's,
giant killers and herringers of hermetasists.
You're listening to the 140th second episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father Interst even Dame.
We can throne in the Palace of Podcasting
in Raleigh, North Kackalaki.
And with me is Father Steven DeYoung,
neck deep in the swarming swamps of Latvia,
the Louisiana.
I am elect here.
You're here in case there were any doubts.
Where did people think you were?
Somewhere else.
Or holy absent perhaps.
All of your absences are holy, I'm sure.
Tell that to my high school friends.
You can get a hall pass.
We are live everybody.
We're live.
that starting in the second half, Mike.
eating spam from the canned again will be taking your calls.
The one who brought me up sold me to a certain rota in Rome.
Many years later I met her again, and I began to love her.
Some time later I saw her bathing in the river Tyber, and I gave her my hand and let her
out of the river.
When I saw her beauty I thought to myself and said, I would be happy if I had a wife of such
beauty in a manner.
It was the only thing I thought, nothing more.
Sometime later as I was going to Kume and praising the creatures of God as they are so great and remarkable and powerful
While I was walking along I fell asleep and a spirit took me and carried me through a certain pathless region
Through which a man could not walk
But enough about your early 20s
We're talking about tonight
It does sound a little bit like my early 20s
Uh
Yeah, that's the beginning. That's the beginning.
of the separate of Hermes and also an excerpt from Father Stevens' diary. A text commonly collected
into a volume usually titled the Apostolic Fathers and if you happen to be making your way through the
Apostolic Fathers and you come to this work you might wonder just what it is you've gotten yourself
into because it's so different from the rest of the texts in that book. But as you're looking at
those texts and thinking of them as a kind of set.
You should remember that it's modern editors that
stick them in a book together, right? So it's kind of largely based on their rough contemporary
contemporary raneity, man. I know it was not going to get that word right, contemporary raneity
in the second century. Although actually, I think that there is the idea that the Dita
key or the Didadac is first century, is that is that the general convention now? Everyone
thinks that maybe maybe okay
was a very pregnant pause. You have built suspense. You can, you know, yeah, right from set
up to pay off, you've got to indeed indeed. Actually, in the chat, someone's predicting
that we're now a step closer to doing an in-on episode. But don't you guys know that
that could mean the end of the podcast is that what you really want, you know? Yes, perhaps
there is already an agreement that that will be the very last episode
this program. It could be, it could be. So okay, Shepard of Hermes. Who wrote this thing?
I mean, who is this, is Hermes the author? Yes. Okay, who is Hermes? Do we even know who
this, I would make you drag, drag every bit of information out of me this up and down.
I'm not asking you.
There's no question.
Yeah, that might be good.
You know, you could leave the witness.
So yeah, so it is a person named Hermes and so that the question is, you know, who
that is not a super uncommon name in the Roman world, a version of Hermes, right?
Right. And so there is actually a Hermes who has mentioned in the New Testament.
and he's even made
the New Testament is living in Rome.
Okay.
And that's in Romans 16, verse 14.
So, Romans 16 is the end of Romans.
St. Paul is doing his say hello to So-and-so,
give my greetings to So-and-so.
Yeah, the big list at the end.
That concluding part of the epistle
and he mentions a Hermus there.
And so there's a few people,
the most noteworthy of them being origin
Who?
concluded that that was the Hermes who wrote the Shepherd of Hermes.
And people should note that title, right?
Everybody knows it as the Shepherd of Hermes these days.
But the actual title of the work is just the Shepherd.
Yeah.
The Of Hermes is like by Hermes, right?
Right.
or write like if you if you see the mini series that it's Stephen
the stand, right? Like the title is the stand. So this is like Hermes's The Shepherd, right?
John Carpenter's The Thing, right? So yeah, Origin, handful of other people concluded that,
but we actually know with a pretty fair degree of certainty who it actually was who wrote it.
because
of a little text, it is a little text.
It's a piece of text that we found,
this is the scholarly we found the Royal...
Editorial?
Yeah, it's not like me and a bunch of other kids
that have been with the dog, right?
We like scholarship, right?
um found this uh
text inserted into the back of another codex. And it's the text called the
Meritorian Canon. And the reason it's called the Meritorian Canon is not that
it's like Canon, like Canon laws, but Canon, like it's a listing of the books of
scripture. So let's say Canon list for scripture. And pretty much everybody
dates that now to around AD 170.
the Canon list. And it is the earliest Canon list we have that lists the 27 books of the New Testament that now make up everybody's New Testament.
That's why it's especially noteworthy. That's why you'll normally see it mentioned in textbooks and secondary literature and that kind of thing.
thing. But it also it it comments on some other books that some people
to be canonical and others didn't. One of the books it comments on is the
shepherd of Hermes and it says that it's not canonical but it doesn't just
stop there right so I mean you'd expect to find with a lot of the apostolic
fathers like the epistle of Barnabas not canonical right but it goes on and
says that it's not recognized being part of the canon.
because it's not apostolic, it was written recently by the brother of Pius, the Bishop of Rome,
who is now known as Pope Pius I, which would place its writing in the 140s.
So if the Burtory cannons were written around 170 and the Shepherd of Hermus was written in the 140s,
40s, that would indeed be resum-
That would be like us writing about something that was written, talking about something that
was written in the early 2000s.
We would say that's fairly recently.
So that's a pretty good peg, right, to hang our hat on.
That's roughly contemporary testimony to who wrote it.
So there's every reason to believe that that's accurate.
it and that this Hermes is a brother, is Pius's brother, and that Pius was a bishop of Rome.
We know from the text itself, including you heard part of the, in the bit that Father
Andrew Red, that he was a freed Roman slave.
mentioned the party red mentioned him having been sold that's as a slave.
But now he was free because he's going on journeys and things.
After having attained his freedom, he we find out in the course of the text had started
a family and had become relatively at least wealthy as a merchant.
He'd become a member of the merchant class in and around Rome.
And it's done well.
Although later the text will also read that at some point he had suffered a kind of financial calamity in his business dealings.
And part of what goes on in some of the texts is him sort of reckoning with that and how he understands why that happened.
The city of Kumei that was also mentioned in that part of the text.
That's the place where he receives his visions, is on the road near that city.
That city is near modern day Naples, Italy, not Naples, Florida.
Not Naples, Florida.
He's not.
And so the shepherd, as we mentioned, is the title.
And the shepherd is an angelic figure.
appears in the text itself, with whom Hermes interacts. So the shepherd is both the title
and the shepherd is a quote-unquote character. We can pause here and talk for a second,
right? Because one of the questions I think is going to be engendered if we don't address it,
Right. Tonight, one of the questions that I think will be asked pretty quickly.
is how literally should we take this? Yeah right?
I mean, I don't know. Right? Well, you and I mean that in a sense that like,
are we to understand? Right? Like we understand when we read the book of
Revelation that St. John is writing about a vision that he actually had. Right?
And he had this vision in this place at a point in time.
This is a thing that really happened
and he records the vision, right?
Yeah, versus is this some kind of just,
like is it just a literary form?
Like he's writing a green vision.
Right now.
So are we to understand that this person Hermes
really had these visions and is recording them
as accurately as he can
or is this a literary device
where he's using this to just communicate certain things.
Right now.
And...
I'm going to give you the response that you may not be expecting and that's that I think
this is meant to be taken literally.
Okay.
I mean, I think, yeah.
I'll see why not.
Like, I don't see, like nothing about this is unbelievable as a set of visions that a
second-century Christian might have.
Yes.
The only reason to think otherwise is if you have some kind of pre-existing theological
commitment.
that. Right. So there are folks out there who believe that such visions stopped. Yeah.
70 AD or at the close of the Apostolic era with the death of the last Apostle. Right. Or some
variation thereof. Right. And that such things didn't continue happening in the church. Yeah.
And those views, those various views are generally grouped in the category.
cessationism. And then views where they don't stop are referred to as continuationist.
That's such the kind of things like this that we see in the New Testament continue through
the history of the church. Ironically, most like pen-
of the castles who you talked to today and charismatic folks who you talked to today will
sit will describe themselves as continuationists. But if you go back to the Toronto blessing
and you go back to the Azusa street, like all the people who started the modern charismatic
movement, we're all restorations. Yes, they believed that it had stopped and that
you know, God was doing a new thing in the words of DC talk.
these last days right because they were
also those groups early on those groups were also very committed to the idea that Christ was about to return
imminently and that that's why these gifts had come back. Right. So but if you want an actual
to say an actual continuation as view, you can look no further than the Orthodox Church. Right. And to be
fair, our Roman Catholic friends also take this view. Right. That throughout church history there have been
and miraculous healing.
including people racing the dead. There have been people who have had visions from God, right? This is not
something limited or confined. So that being our view, right, I see no reason that the text
seems to want to be taken literally, and I see no reason to not take it literally, right, on that basis.
and the weather or not the test.
Next is canonical, whether or not it's part of the New Testament because it's not, and it's
clearly not.
Yeah, I don't, does anyone say that it is?
Not really.
Yeah.
It's clearly not.
That has no effect on this question.
Right.
Us saying that this is legitimately him recording visions he had from God is not the same thing as saying it's part of the Bible.
That's another presupposition that a lot of our Protestant friends may have, right?
Is that any kind of anything that could be called revelation that comes from God is automatically
scriptural in some sense.
And no, that's not the case either, right?
Especially not in the Orthodox Church, right?
Where we believe the Holy Spirit has inspired ecumenical councils.
Right now.
there are other things, right? So yeah, so all that is to say, to preempt that question
when we're done, like, is this real? This or however it might be phrased, we are operating
under the belief that, yes, it is. But this is something that really happened to Hermes,
brother of pies the first, right, and that he is recording it. Right.
So the basic structure of the shepherd of Hermes
is there are five visions followed by 12 commandments
followed by 10 parables.
And it's kind of nested.
And what I mean by nested is that the 12 commandments
the ten parables sort of are the kind of...
content of the fifth vision. Yeah. Which reads most of the text is the fifth
vision. Right. The vast majority of the text is the fifth vision. But you can
see that kind of nesting like in the book of Revelation. So you get to like the
seventh trumpet and the first seal gets opened. Right. So like the the seven
seals are like nested in
the seventh trumpet of the seventh trumpets, right?
Yeah.
Hyper hypertextual on some level.
So that kind of nesting is not in common.
Now that said, I just made a comparison to the book of revelation.
But technically speaking, the shepherd of Hermes is not apocalyptic literature.
Okay.
I mean, it reads that way.
Like you get to, you know, the very beginning you get this and a spirit came and took
me along paths that no man can speak, you know, that kind of thing.
very psychopompas I don't know if psychopompas is a word it is today father it is
today okay okay it's like a really arrogant lunatic yes would be psychopompas
But the, and so there are things that we associate like Father Ed.
just pointed out, there are things in the tax that we associate with apocalyptic literature
like someone having visions, right? Someone being carried by a spirit, this sort of language.
But if you think about things that are clear cut apocalyptic literature.
Okay, so the Book of Revelation, clear cut upon.
the Apocalypse of Peter that we did an episode about at one point.
I'm pretty sure.
Or it was part of an episode.
Or it had a whole episode.
That sounds right.
Yeah.
We've talked about on the show before.
We'll leave it there.
The Apocalypse of Peter.
Clear cut apocalyptic literature.
The book of Enic, which we have not yet talked about on the show.
In spite of that being all we talk about on the show.
We've made a...
Right. That is clear cut apocalyptic literature. When you look at the sort of structure of it and the nature of it, it is about a person led by a psychopomp led by a guide.
Right, going on a journey through the cosmos that is somehow revelatory about deeper levels
of reality.
And then,
and then communicating what was seen on that journey.
And that's not quite what happens in the Shepard of Hermes.
What happens in the Shepard of Hermes is a series of visions
and then commandments and parables, imagery, these kind of things,
that are much closer to what you find in the Old Testament Proof.
Most of the Old Testament prophetic books are not apocalyptic. There's some apocalyptic portions of Daniel and Zechariah is apocalyptic.
So there's some of that, but those are in the, you may have noticed from the two examples I gave, those are the, the, some of the latest books of the Old Testament, right?
Yeah. And then pretty much the latest of the Hebrew Bible.
where you start getting apocalyptic.
So that apocalyptic format develops during the second temple period.
It develops out of prophetic literature, but it's not identical to it.
And so the shepherd of Hermos fits more neatly into the genre of prophecy
than into the genre of apocalyptic per se.
And interestingly, we didn't mention it.
before, but the Mediterranean canon in addition to saying that the shepherd of hermice was
not canonical because it had been written recently, it also said, described the shepherd as
a prophetic book and said the number of the prophets was closed, meaning the section of
the Bible called the prophets in the Old Testament was already established by the
140s. You couldn't add to that. Right. And so it was identifying it as being of this prophetic genre.
But now that we've said that, right, this raises another question. Right. Well, then wait a
minute. How can we take it literally? How can we, right, if profit per se is an old testament thing,
if that's how we understated with the murdering cannon.
saying and that there aren't anymore, right? And we just celebrated the
Nativity of St John the Forerunner, right? And is he not the crown of the prophets? He's like the last
one, right? Well, yes and no, right? He's the last of the Old Testament prophets.
But if you read the New Testament closely, for example, in the book of Acts, you find this prophet
egg of a
who shows up twice in the book of Acts.
To talk about prophetic visions he's received.
One predicting a famine, the other one he comes and does prophetic actions very much
in keeping with the way profits acted in the Old Testament to tell St. Paul that he's going
to be arrested.
Right. And, uh, and have to endure suffering.
So there's a new
Testament prophet Agabus after St. John the Forerunner. Yeah. Yeah. And St. Paul talks about prophecy is
one of the gifts of the spirit in first Corinthians. Right. Yep. So and of course, you know, when St. Peter
Preaches on Pentecost.
It says that
Joel too has been fulfilled.
He says, you know, your young men will have visions and your old men will dream dreams.
That doesn't sound like you say that's over, right?
Right.
So, this kind of visionary thing, not only is it a fact that our belief is Orthodox Christians
that this has continued in the era of Christ Church, post-Penocost.
But that's what the New Testament.
So if we accept those things in the New Testament, then this happening in the 140s with Hermas, again, is not all that weird.
Right? It's all that weird. And so the Mediterranean canon is not talking about whether it's legitimate or not, whether it's good or not, whether it's true or not, the Mediterranean canon is talking about whether it's part of the New Testament, whether it's part of the Bible.
And the answer to that for the word Torin Cannon is
pretty much everybody else in the ancient church is no it's not part of the Bible right
it's not part of the New Testament so that being said that it was it was very clear that it was
not part of the Bible it was still incredibly popular in the ancient church
So you will sometimes hear, in fact, somebody I don't know, I don't watch
the YouTube chat. So I don't know if anyone's doing this or someone maybe getting ready to
call in and be like, but wait, I thought it was, I thought there were people who thought
it was canonical, right? And that's going to be because they read something like, oh,
it's in codex syniaticus. Right. At the end of the New Testament is not a cannot, it's
not a book that defines a canon. Right. Right. So the fact that you
find a Bible codex and it has a text in it that does not mean that whoever compiled that
physical book that physical codex thought that that was part of the canon.
I mean if you own a North-Earth-Earth study Bible there's a bunch of stuff in there that's
not canonical.
Yes.
Like all the notes and the Mac.
Apocryphal.
And morning and evening prayers in the back.
Yes.
in the Orthodox study Bible.
So that's not right.
And so you find that very commonly.
And just to talk about codex cytianicus in particular,
right, in particular, the old testament of codex cytianicus,
at the end of the old testament, you find a bunch
of interesting things like the prayer of manasse,
which is like a longish paragraph.
Right, that is on and that is not on anyone's any canon lists of the old testament
But it's in there in Kodak Sinaiaticus. I guess what it is. It's a liturgical prayer
The Orthodox Church we still use it in great compliment
As usually celebrated you're probably good if you go to great compliment in the US odds are good
You're going during great length and that's where you hear the prayer of Manasseh, right?
But that's in there because it's a liturgical prayer.
And if you're paying a ton of money and it costs a ton of money to get a codex made, right?
Adding a few pages is a relatively small cost compared to the cost of getting the book done.
So getting some of the prayers from church, there's a whole section of essentially all of the
biblical oeds are added at the end of the Old Testament and codex on Aadicus, meaning
you
They've already been like an Exodus 15,
you have the song of the sea in context.
And then it's also reproduced
at the end of the Old Testament
because it was sung liturgically in churches.
All the Oads, including the Ninth Ode
is there at the end of the Old Testament.
The Ninth Ode being the Magnificat in St. Luke's Gospel.
That doesn't mean the person who put together
Codexanaticus thought that Luke one
was part of the Old Testament.
I mean, these are the surgical inclusions.
I mean, that's what it is.
So all kinds of things get included in codexes,
in codices, right?
In codices that nobody thought were canonical.
So that is not actually evidence.
Now, well, we'll come back to that.
What I was about to say.
So you don't really find any church fathers.
Now, St. Aaronnaeus is the first earliest church father
we have who mentions the shepherd.
And that makes a-
lot of sense since uh senior
NAS of Leon was also writing
around 170 AD or at the same
time as the
Viratory and Canon. Yeah, that
basically contemporaneous.
Yeah. And so he's writing
about something that came out
25, 30 years earlier. You'd
expect him to be to be the
first one to mention it. He's
also in the West, obviously,
and this is coming from Rome.
So uh and and he quotes it in
of authoritative way, even though he doesn't say it is written. He's not quoting it in
a scripture, but he quotes it as being an authoritative statement. So that tells you how popular it
got, how quickly. And how it was viewed almost immediately. Clement of Alexandria and origin both
quote from it authoritatively, although as we mentioned, origin was a little confused about who
who wrote it, but had the text.
It saw it as an authoritative.
text both St. Athanasius and UCBS of Cessaria, St. Athanasius being the more important one
here for this purpose, recommended using the shepherd of Hermes for Christian catechism.
Hmm. And notably, St. Athanasius's Paschal letter, isn't that the earliest list of the
27 or at least extant list extant list of the 27 books new test.
Well, yeah, where it's proclaimed as don't read any other books. Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
But so, but that shows you, right, that gives you an idea of the kind of authority it had, right?
So say, Nathanations say use this for cataclyzing people and how to live a Christian life, right, shows you, well, he doesn't, again, think it's scripture.
its scripture.
Right, but he sees it as authoritative and having this important
Use right within the church
Saint Jerome makes a comment at one point that
Because it was quoted against him in something he was arguing about
That
The shepherd wasn't as popular as it used to be
That's a very Saint Jerome. I can see that someone's like someone's quoting into is like look that that Texas
just not as popular as it used to be.
Yeah, yeah, who reads that anyway, that's so 350 man like coming at me with that. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I
If you've read much st. Jerome, you can totally yeah. Oh absolutely. I mean, Jerome very famously is the guy who
Depending on how you read it essentially blames polygeneism on overconsumption of haggis. Yeah. Yeah. And I mean true story folks. Yeah, he was he was from up there
Um, some...
But even though St. Jerome talks about how it's not as popular as it used to be, St. John
Cashin, who's his rough contemporary, cites it all the time, particularly when he's talking
about like it is institutes, well, I have the conferences, but when he's talking about
monastic formation and that kind of thing, he cites it just as the pastor, which of course
He's writing in Latin.
So, yeah, that's the word for shepherd.
Equates the path.
just commonly. Right. So it's still popular enough for him. Right. And all the way into the
ninth century, St. Nicholas, the confessor of Constantinople, who has become probably much more
well-known in the Orthodox Church due to be mentioning him all the time on this show. It in one of my books.
I've been getting to the ninth century.
Lists.
The Shepherd of Hermes and his books to be read privately section of his
Canon list
The text is the most popular between the second and fifth from the time of its writing in the second century until the fifth century
And a wide variety of church fathers of people will cite it
authoritatively
throughout that those centuries and then it still gets cited
but less commonly as you go forward,
past the fifth century.
It was originally written in Greek.
We do not have the whole text in Greek.
Yeah, there's some lacuna here and there.
I think even what we do have, right?
Yeah, in the Greek, yeah.
Yeah, in the Greek text.
But it was translated almost immediately into Latin
as you might expect, given where it was written.
better.
And so we have complete Latin text.
So in some cases we can reconstruct the Greek
in those, look at it.
And we also have translations of it
into coptic, Ethiopic, Arabic, Georgian,
get ready for it.
Middle Persian.
Yeah.
I mean, that many languages spread across
that
geography suggests that it was a ridiculously popular text.
Yes.
And especially when you consider that the middle Persian copy was not found in Persia,
the middle Persian copy was found in what's now part of China.
Yeah, which I mean, we know that the Assyrians did mission work in that area.
Yeah.
Given given the other text it was found with, most people think that the particular
little person copy was being
used by manakies. But that doesn't mean they're the ones who made it. And there were also
as Father Andrew just mentioned, Church of the East people operating in that language
and through that region as well. But so yes, that is just a huge geographic and linguistic
sweep. The one oddity in there, the language you might have expected me to name and I
dented.
Syria. Yeah. And we don't have any copies in Syria. And no one knows why there are journal
articles about this. Ha about why theorizing about why the Syrian act church in particular
would not have liked. The Shabbat of purpose. But we don't actually know, right? Like
nobody left a note saying, Hey, we decided not to translate this into Syria, because XYZ
Right.
And maybe we will find one. You'd ever know, right? There may have been one just to have it found it because it wasn't as popular there.
But it is it is a sort of oddity that I mean it's also just a reality that texts from the ancient world.
You know, we've lost most of them. So yeah, who knows?
Who knows?
Making the word of a bunch of copies.
Fibing a Christian text in Arabic but not Syriac is weird.
Yeah.
Right.
Thank you.
So before we go on and sort of dig deeper into the contents of the book itself, I want
to make a comment about maybe some further comments at this point about what we've been
talking about with with canonicity, right? And we've talked before.
I want to get directly at something that we've talked about by a bout I mean sort of around the past, right?
And I want to put a finer point on it. And that's sort of a question, right? So a lot of our discussions of canon
of the canon of scripture, regardless of who's having them, whether it's Orthodox folks having them, Roman Catholic folks having them,
Protestant folks having them.
or discussions between those groups about the canon of scripture are very much formed
by Protestantism, even if Protestants are discussing it, or directly involved in the
discussion.
And so in part that's because of some history, right?
So it's a few.
to Protestant apologetic folks online have kind of gotten onto this recently that they're
like, hey, wait a minute.
Did you know that there's some vagaries around the Old Testament canon between different
Orthodox churches, right?
Is it that weird?
Isn't that crazy?
I'm looking for some pearls here so that I can clutch them.
Yeah.
Is it that bizarre?
Maybe we could use this as a point, right, of criticism, and they sort of can't fathom
how that could work, right?
But I'm going to argue that the Orthodox Church has never really cared that much about
that.
Right.
Like that hasn't been a big issue for us and that's why it hasn't happened.
Yeah, because our understanding what the Bible is is not that it's this set of words from
which we derive our religion.
Yes.
and that while it is...
Right? Different in various ways than all other books, right? And there are things that are
scripture and things that are not, right? That doesn't mean it's wholly other. Yes.
Christians, we aren't like Muslims or some Hasidic Jews who think that the Torah or the Quran.
have like eternally existed. I feel like there's going to be some some subset of KJV only
IFB people that believe that. Oh, there are. But I said Christians. Oh,
five. All right. You're throwing as persons that who's a Christian who's not fun. I hear
about you on Twitter. You say these things all the time. I'm just saying some of those folks
far afield from the Christian religion as it has historically existed on this earth.
So, yeah, so the Christianity does not teach that, right?
Including, Magisterial Protestantism did not teach that, right?
Any of that weirdness, right?
So, yeah, so we did feel it needed to do that.
Rome didn't feel the need.
To establish an old Testament canon authoritatively until Trent
Yeah, which I mean that's
Late medieval. Yes, and what was Trent? Trent was a response to Protestantism
There you go
Okay, so I mean it could it be said that in some sense that the way that we all think of canon is basically because of the
Reformation. Yes, it's because of Protestantism
Yeah, it's because of Protestantism. We had a very different understanding.
of it. Right? St. Nicholas for us, here he comes again with his list. Right? It's not just
that he listed. Here's the canonical books. Here's the books to be read privately. Here's
the books not to be read. He had a list. He had a sublist in there between canonical,
between read publicly and read privately of books that were read publicly by some churches and not
others. Yeah, even ninth century.
And if you look at that list, there were still churches in communion with all the other churches.
Part of the one holy Catholic Orthodox church, whenever adjectives we want to apply, right, who were reading publicly in the liturgy from the apocalypse of St. Peter.
So technically speaking, which of course is the best kind of correct, right?
Greg is the best guy to correct.
That's kind of correct.
The apocalypse of Peter was being scripture for those churches at that time.
Yeah.
They give true.
And for St. Nicholas, it wasn't a problem.
Yeah.
Right.
We have at least one 12th century codex.
It has first and second clemen in it in the New Testament.
Now, you might say to me, but Father Steven, you just said it being in a codex.
It doesn't mean they thought it was canonical.
And I say, you're correct, but not only our first and second clemen in the codex, they're
in the dictionary for the New Testament.
appointed to be read in church on particular.
Yes, they're in the lectionary in the twelfth.
century. Wow. So that's just a couple examples. Canonicity, the Canon thing is way
more messy than anybody wants to admit. And it's way more messy than it can be for
solar scripturative function.
Oh, yeah.
Big time.
Yeah, I was going to say like
I know people do it, but I just, I cannot wrap my head around knowing anything almost about
the history of the development of canon and thinking that somehow works with solar
scriptura.
I just, I don't see how that could possibly be.
But I'm not the one to defend so I know.
I know.
Yeah.
So when you get to the Reformation, it's one of the five souls.
and you get to Soluscriptura, Soluscriptura kind of requires not only that there be set books
of the Old and New Testament with firmly established borders, which hadn't been before that.
And so then Rome makes their own list over against the Protestant list and the East continues
the function as we always have, right?
that it requires, if you know anything about Soluscript, the Doctorate of Soluscriptura,
the actual doctrine that's actually taught in the Reformation, those texts have to be self-attesting.
Hmm.
It has to be clear in some way that those books and not other books.
Yeah, because no matter how you, no matter how you understand Soluscriptura, right, whether
It's the most kind of reductionist.
I read it in my Bible, therefore it's true,
KJV only independent fundamentals Baptist,
or it's the most high church liturgically oriented
magisterial Protestant saying it means
by scripture alone, and they accept all these other things.
When you make it that kind,
when you use it as a standard in that way,
then it must have clear borders that...
theoretically should always have been there and cannot be changed.
Yeah. Yeah. It should have attested. You should be able to look at historically
it attesting to itself. Right. Yeah.
Yeah. The reception history. And you don't see that. No, it's way more messy than that.
Yeah. There's not even you can't even come up with a kind of landmark as trail of blood
version of that. Yeah, just not a thing. And so it does it work.
Right? And so this is how, as we've said before, the idea of canonicity, especially in
Protestant circles, becomes a wonder as zero. Right? Either it's Bible, but it's a hundred
percent true, inherent, literal, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, or it's zero. Not only is
Is it not Bible, but it's essentially worthless?
said, who cares? Right? Now you may object to me, but Father Stephen, you are
strong-anning. School of Scripture, because the Magistrate of Reformers said there
were secondary authorities. There were these various things, creeds, confessions,
right, church fathers, even texts, right, that have this sort of secondary authority status.
Right. And my question or my pushback on that is always, can they actually function like that in
a Protestant setting though? Yeah. So yes, the Majesty of Reform Reformers certainly said that.
And I think especially Luther and Calvin themselves and even Bollinger and some of the right
immediate reformers and there's actually sort of practice that.
That's why you can see Calvin Luther at all accepting a lot of things
from church tradition, from the church fathers, from other things
that latter generations of Protestants and evangelicals now, especially now today, no longer accept.
We can start with infant baptism and go from there.
Right.
uh...
perpetual virginity
the theatokos. List goes on and on and on. Right. These things that the reformers accepted that now
are verboten and catholic and bad and antibiblical if you ask somebody in the present day
that Lutheran Calvin had no problem with. Right. So and that's because
while they held to this and they affirmed this nothing can function as a secondary authority
because
you are always able to just read scripture differently and say, no, that's not
scriptural. Yeah, I mean, you know that they're doing this when they say, well,
nothing is above scripture. And I'm like, what you mean by that, and maybe
don't know you mean by that is nothing is above my interpretation of scripture.
right right because Calvin Luther
swingway,
Bollinger,
all would have told you that infant baptism was biblical.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, some of Swingley's followers.
Yeah, I don't know, I don't know about Bollinger,
but all those guys would have also told you
the perpetual virginity of the Virgin Mary was biblical.
Yes.
That's right.
We have actual votes.
Some of Swingley's followers said,
I don't see any infants getting baptized in the Bible.
Yeah.
And so they threw the baby out with a baptismal water.
I know that's clever.
Come on, man.
Nice.
Chrissy chopper.
Okay.
I'll think so.
We'll be writing that one down to use next time.
Yeah.
Coffee hour.
So, right.
So, so, that's happened on and on and on, right?
is a chain of things. Right?
And so you get to where we are now where, you know, the list of beliefs that make up mere Christianity, the sort of non-negotiables, the Christian non-negotiables, that list gets shorter and shorter every 10 years.
Hmm.
Right. It never goes the other way.
Nothing has ever been added to the list in Protestantism.
Right, but go pick up the fundamentals from the 1920s and see how many of those people would consider negotiable today
Hmm, yeah.
In evangelical circles, 100 years later.
The list always gets shorter, never longer.
So there's not a way for things to function with a secondary authority,
okay, within, within process.
So this gives us, in the Orthodox Church, two great advantages.
Number one, we can let the Bible be the Bible.
We don't have a theological commitment that says
the scriptures have to be a certain way. They have to be structured a certain way. They have to
function a certain way. Only certain genres can be included. Everything has to be literal. Everything
has to be certain. We don't have any of those commitments. We could just let the Bible be what it is.
Whatever we learn about canonicity, and hey, it's a little flexible around the edges. That's not a
a problem for us. We could just let the Bible be the Bible. You don't have to try and hammer it.
do a hole it doesn't really fit through, right? Because of our our doctrinal commitments.
But we also can have something like the shepherd of Hermes function as a secondary authority.
So when we talk about these things being secondary authorities, because what I'm trying to
be clear on here is. I'm trying to bring some clarity to what hopefully every
orthodox
Lysiter already has heard from somewhere at some point, is that within the Orthodox Church,
Scripture is part of Holy Tradition, but it is preeminent within Holy Tradition.
So I'm trying to get here into what that means.
And what that means is, Scripture has a primary authority, it is of a primary authoritative nature.
other things
like the church fathers, like even the councils,
like the Shepherd of Hermas, right, the Apostolic fathers,
have a secondary authority.
But what do we mean by secondary?
We mean by secondary here,
something parallel to what we mean when we talk about primary
and secondary literature in scholarship.
Right.
So primary literature in sc-
scholarship. If you're studying, uh, if you're studying
Hegel, okay, then primary literature is Hegel's own works.
Right. So phenomenology of spirit is a primary source, a
primary text for the study of Hegel, because Hegel wrote it.
there
box up
about Hagle or journal articles about Hagle, about the phenomenology of
Spirit are secondary literature. Secondary because they're about their
interpreting, they're understanding, they're applying, they're working with the
primary text. Right. And hypothetically, you could have tertiary texts too, where
somebody's writing.
book about a book about Hagle. But that's we won't go down that rabbit trail. So when we talk about
holy tradition, being a way of reading the scriptures, a way of interpreting the scriptures,
this is what we mean by secondary authority. It is full authority, right? Meaning this is the
the correct way.
to read and understand the Scriptures. It is the authoritative way to do that.
Right? All other ways to do that are incorrect by virtue of not being this way.
Right? But that is secondary to the Scriptures themselves.
Right? And that's why you find all of these statements, the statements that our Protestant friends like to point to and try to claim our
solar scriptura among the fathers.
Right, let's say things like the Council of Nicaeo was just summer...
and explaining scripture. It was all based on scripture. Yes,
but it is the authoritative way,
inspired by the Holy Spirit, directed by the Holy Spirit, to correctly read the scriptures.
Therefore, if you read the scriptures in some way that denies the doctrine of the Holy Trinity,
you are reading the scriptures incorrectly.
and you cannot appeal
to the scriptures themselves because of the council. Because the council has authoritatively said,
this is the way the scriptures are to be read. Vis-a-vis the Holy Trinity. So it's not that your conscience and
your reading of scripture are sacrosaic to have the highest authority as in the right of private judgment
in classical Protestantism, that is actually the absolute lowest level of authority. All authority of the church trumps your personal private opinion.
All right, everything trumps that.
Yeah, like it's amazing to me that people really believe.
Honestly, like sincerely, they really believe what you know,
that the captors would call.
soul competency. The idea that each person is truly authoritative in and of
himself in interpreting the scriptures. I think it's really, really, really,
really clear. You can get it wrong. I think that's a lot of really at least four.
Yeah. Yeah. grammar check won't let me do that, but you got to
once you've asked her the English language, you can use it how you like.
Ah, there we go.
It's like jazz, right? You learn all the rules so you can break them creatively. Exactly.
So yeah, that's... And so the reason we're talking about that here is I think the
shepherd of herm is this sort of this perfect case for this. We're going to come back to this
a little in the third half when we talk about the importance after we've gone through.
some of the contents that we talk about, some of the issues and controversy.
surrounding the shepherd of Hermas, I think it'll be clear why we wanted to talk about this here,
but this is a broader issue than just the shepherd of Hermas. The shepherd of Hermas is just a test case,
right, for how different parts of the tradition function, what it means that we say in the Orthodox
Church that the scriptures have a primacy of place within a holy tradition, but are inseparable from
from Holy Tradition.
So hopefully that's clarifying for folks out there.
in TV land.
Well, everybody in TV land, that's the first half of this episode of Lord of
Spirit's podcast on the Shepherd of Hermes. We're gonna take a short break and
we'll be right back. Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirit's. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
What's the deal with the legendary mythic stories of the Orthodox Christian tradition?
Join Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Deacon Sarifim Richard Rowland at the Orthodox Legendary
at St. Ignatius in Tiochin Orthodox Church in Franklin, Tennessee, July 31 through August
2.
Together, we'll hear stories spanning the saints' defeats of dragons to an unlikely saint
called the Fox and we will gather together for
Church and to eat, learn more and register at ancientfaith.com slash events.
That's ancientfaith.com slash events.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
I think that might be the shortest commercial break ever.
because
the guy reading the ad and read it really fast.
Chris, there wasn't a lot of coffee to it.
It is apparently now referring to himself
as the third person.
I mean, I don't know.
I didn't write the copy.
Did I?
Maybe I don't remember you, Bob Dole.
Is that what's going on here?
Well, well, that's just waves of nostalgia rolling over me with that reference.
Actually, yeah, that was about to say it's not Bob Dole.
It's John McKee.
that I share birthday with, not Bob Dole.
In my head, they're the same person.
I think you're becoming him with this whole early bedtime old man to make vibe you've
got going on now.
Simon, our producer assures me that I'm not the one who wrote the copy for that ad, so
there we go.
I'm not responsible.
The fact that you didn't remember is just one more thing to add to the old man, damn it
live.
That's true.
I remember the things that are really important for me to remember now.
It's just a shorter and shorter list.
Like when to take your pills and when the early bird dinner ends at Bob Evans, all
those important things.
That's right.
I mean, you and I are now both old enough to join ARP, not that I intend to.
I would be amused if you had.
Well no, because you have to go through the joining thing and I don't get any discounts
till 55.
Oh, oh, is that true?
Yes.
Ha.
That's right.
Let me tell you kids out there.
Father Andrew and I are the worst period of life.
Right.
We got the click and knees.
We got the noises we make when we sit in a chair and get back up.
Yeah.
And we got no senior discounts yet.
Four more years.
This is just like the opposite.
Whatever the opposite of the sweet spot is.
The bitter spot.
That's where we're at right now.
How do you really even want like the senior coffee?
McDonald's. I mean, yes, I want really discount and free things. Yes,
constantly matter how crappy they are. You don't understand. So my wife and I
do. I don't know what it's like to be Dutch. I don't know my wife and I make
lists of places in town that give free things on your birthday. And we make
the circuit on our birthdays.
Wow. So levels to this, my friend.
Well, all right, well, we do have a caller on the other end of the
line and I mean the name looks very French to me so I'm going to say Gion. So either
from Canada or California he just wrote CA so I'm not sure which it is so welcome Laura
Spears podcast.
Hi, it's from California.
California.
And what is your name that I mispronounced it utterly?
You know, stop trying to get on. I, you know,
you know, American English.
So does Gium Mike spelled it like Robert Leom. Yeah, yeah, Mike spelled it very badly. He didn't write Gium. He wrote
Gium like with an end on the end. Oh, I'm thinking about firing him. What do you think Gium? Should we fire Mike for his failures to spell correctly?
French names. I never watched Benson in it. He seemed on top. I don't know. He seemed on top. What to expect?
It seemed fine.
I don't know.
Anyway.
way. We'll just have to review that later. So, so what's up in
Cal if see the thing is with that French name, I thought I
would I saw that C.A. I'm like, well, this seems like Canada
seems like Canada. Yes. But it turns out you're in California.
And there isn't Ontario, California, that to be confused with
Ontario, Canada. Is there a Quebec, California? That's the
real question. I don't. I hope they hate me and Quebec because
my French name, but I cannot speak French actually. So I'm
Yeah.
I'm no.
Okay.
The California has a great mall.
Yeah.
And is is is the secret airport.
Like if you're flying into like Orange County or you're flying into the inland empire,
you have a much easier time getting in and out of Ontario airport.
You know, there's an Ontario high.
And it is also the mall town in its region.
Huh?
There's something about Ontario's that makes for a good malls or just makes for malls
I don't know if they could or not, but so what is on your mind, Guillaume, from not Ontario, California?
Yeah, so my main question is on the shepherd of Permanence, and I just, by way of background,
I feel like with a lot of these texts, I was always raised, I was raised Baptist, so I would always
hear about these texts, and they would just say, well, there's something in all of them
and it's theoretical, right?
And then the one I...
actually read a lot of them, I kind of felt like mostly people were misunderstanding something
that was in the text.
The one I heard about the shepherd of Hermit was that, or the shepherd, was that it blurs
the lines between the spirit and the sun because when there's the interpretation given
of the vision of this woman, it says,
and the spirit in one...
place I think it even says, Holy Spirit is the sun. And so they say, ah, see, that's,
you know, it's blurring the persons. But from what I understand, I think, but my, I have
it in Greek, but my Greek is not great. It seems like you can read what they're saying.
It's just saying you saw a spirit and that spirit was the sun. And so it's not actually
boring.
aligns between two persons of the Trinity. I don't quite know the text well enough to
be sure about that. I wasn't sure if perhaps Father Steven might know.
Yeah. We are actually going to talk about some of this Christology stuff in the third half,
but I mean, yeah, why don't you want to give at least some response now, Father?
At least a tea. Yeah, we are going to get into this more a little
worth barely in the third half.
But yeah, so.
And this is sort of the framework we're going to be getting into in the third half is.
The question should always be, right.
Before you assert that the text is teaching something is,
is this the only way you can read it?
So that's kind of what you did, right?
Like, you looked at the Greek and you're like,
well, that's not necessarily saying that, right?
And there is a perfectly orthodox way to read that.
So why would you read it the other way?
And so in the third half, we're going
to get into a little more about why
sub-scholars read things in certain ways,
based on certain presuppositions.
Yeah.
And what you've pointed to is a good example of that
in this text that we're going to...
develop more there. So you're tracking with us.
Well, that's good.
Do you have a moment for hopefully a quick off topic question?
But I got no more topics that have come up a lot on the show.
Sure, sir.
So in talking about atonement,
and there's been really multiple episodes that have hit it from different angles
and evolve.
and really helpful.
One aspect that I'm a bit confused about,
and I know you mentioned it in one of the episodes,
but it couldn't quite follow how it fit,
was when it came to the curse.
And so it was almost at least the impression I got,
and I could be mistaken was that we don't think
of Christ as a substitute in the sense of his death
as Peter calls him more of...
an example in suffering. But is there a sense in which, if you're not talking about a
tone, if you're specifically talking about the curse, is there a substitutionary element there?
Because we don't usually think of ourselves as enduring the curse beyond the fact that I guess
we do in the sense that we die is death the only part of the curse or the main part of the curse.
I guess I'm not, I'm not sure how to reconcile that part.
of it. Yeah. So I mean the curse is the effects of sin. Right. And dying is not the only
effect of sin. Yeah. But dying materially physically, right? Obviously spiritual death.
Yeah. I mean, all of the things that we suffer in this world are the curse. Yeah. So there's
in what sense did Jesus take all that away?
that we're still experienced so that we wouldn't have to experience it at all. I mean, I don't know
about you, but I experienced the effects of sin in my life, including my own sin, especially my own sin.
But other people sin as well. So, yeah, I mean, in that sense of Jesus did this so that I don't have to, I'm just not seeing it.
I'm just not seeing it. You know, as we've, I can't remember which episode it was,
so it was Father.
But we kind of boil it down to, like, it's clear that we're suffering all these things.
And the one thing that some people would essentially say is that Jesus suffered damn
nations so that we don't have to.
But then you have to say that Jesus was damned.
And then that introduces a big, crystallological problem.
To come back to your first question, the Jesus is a big, crystallological problem is that
how can God be damned?
How can, you know, you split the Trinity that way?
Like, that's a problem.
That's a big problem.
I don't know.
and I remember crack
Yeah, well yeah, in terms of atonement. So I'm going to categorize this in terms of
fleshing it out rather than disagreeing with father Andrew because I'm thanks. You know,
I disagree with every time. As everyone knows, I am super charitable at all times with all people.
So yeah, so in terms of the curse, so there's what the word curse means biblically, right?
But there's also we need to do a little disambiguating between, so there's the curse is in like the curse that Adam receives, right?
Which is what Father Andrew was mainly talking about, right?
Curson that says.
There's also the curse of the law, or the curse of the Torah that St. Paul talks about.
And it is included in one of our prayers that the priest does every liturgy.
or deemed us from the curse of the law by that precious blood.
Right. Yeah. Yeah.
And so that's it. That's a different thing, right? The curse of the Torah, when St. Paul talks
about it is talking about the curses like in Deuteronomy, like 29 and 30, right?
Which was basically the prediction of what happened, the exile, right? Israel in the language of
Ezekiel, Israel had died and was dry bones, remember?
Right?
No.
And the promise was that Israel would be resurrected.
Right.
But Israel had died as a result of the curse of the Torah, not that the Torah was a curse,
but because they did not keep Torah, they received the curses of the Torah.
And so that is also within the broad category of effects of sin, right?
that is sort of the definition of curse. Okay. And so the question is, for Christ, obviously, is
completely free from sin, and so is not under the curse. That's why the church has always been clear
about the idea that the Theotokos did not suffer pain and childbirth. That's not some kind of
of dositism that Christ wasn't really born.
That's because pain and childbirth is a result of the curse.
Right?
That you've received.
So Christ's birth is free from that because he is not under the curse.
In terms of the curse of Adam, we talk about Christ voluntarily taking upon himself the
sinless passions, the blameless passions.
So he voluntarily becomes tired, hungry, thirsty.
Right? All of those things, the weakness of human nature that is the result of the curse that is the result of sin in the world.
But so the question for St. Paul, because St. Paul is positing that Christ also redeems Israel, redeems the people of God collectively from the curse of the Torah.
But how can he do that?
How can he voluntarily...
Take on himself the curse of the Torah without violating the Torah
Yeah, and St Paul's solution to that problem is
Deuteronomy said Kerset is everything that hangs on a tree
Hmm, and so St Paul's answer is that the reason the particular mode of Christ's death is important
Why he chose that way to die is that by dying being hung on a tree
he voluntary
came under the curse of the Torah without violating it. And that allowed him then
to redeem Israel from the curse of the Torah. So the way in which he
redeems is not substitution, it's solidarity. It's participation. And so we are
redeemed from the curse of the Torah in Christ.
We participate in Christ. We're baptized into Christ and put on Christ.
So it's not substitution. It's participation and solidarity.
There you go. I mean, that makes sense to me. Does it make sense to you, Guillaume?
Yeah, I think so. I want to it was also helpful. I think I was kind of squishing together
two senses of curse with, you know, Adam
and the curses of the...
So I think that also helps to parse those and I wasn't really thinking that way before.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, cool. All right. Well, thanks for your call.
We're going to take one more caller and then move on.
So we have Eddie calling from Texas. Eddie, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Hey, thank you for taking my question. Actually, real quick statement.
I just want to let you guys know I'm getting transmitted next month on the 12th.
and all of it.
good. The good thing is
that you guys getting me
through a lot of the
homes and allowing me to
convert to the space.
Thank God. Pray for us.
Congratulations.
Yeah.
I definitely want to thank you guys.
And then I have a question about
in my mind and this is where you can
probably declare me a heretic if I'm wrong on this.
But we don't get to declare people heretics because we're not
Wow.
Eat for yourself.
all the time. Yeah, yeah.
Father and the young does it all the time.
So, uh, I kind of, when I look at extra biblical books that are outside of the canon, you know,
like first climate and and books like that, uh, I kind of give them a kind of stack breakdown.
The letters of polycarps, the letters of Ignatius, the kind of stack rigged them.
If they're closer to the apostles, I give them a lot of primacy.
Where would I put the primacy of the shepherd of Hermos?
of Hermas, because I know like it almost made it in the Bible.
Like, would you put that up?
up there with a letter from Ignatius or a letter from Pauli Carp?
I mean, I don't think it's accurate to say that it almost made into the Bible.
I mean, we spent the beginning of the show essentially saying no one ever called it scripture
and several made a point of saying it wasn't scripture.
But I mean, I think within orthodoxy, even though we don't have a sense of development of
doctrine in this way that like
gradually we came upon the doctrine of the Trinity after having primitive stuff early on.
There is certainly a sense that the early Church Fathers, which is kind of a broad term
that sort of encompasses the first several centuries, that because of their use they have
a kind of greater authority, but there's so many exceptions to that that I could lay
out.
You know, like, you know.
St. Gregory Palamas is a figure from the 14th century, and he's a towering figure.
You know, I couldn't say, well, you know, who needs Palamas? I have St. Basil. Although
St. Gregory Palamas might well say that himself. But yeah, I mean, I think it kind of depends on
what you're using it for. So I would say, especially if you're having conversations with Protestants
and trying to explain to them the early church, some of the stuff from the second century is super
useful.
for that because you can say, look, these are the next generation or two from the apostles
and this is what they believed.
This is what they said.
So it's really very helpful for that purpose, I think.
That's exactly where I was going with that.
Yeah.
Like my go to for that is always Ignatius because he's directly connected to the apostles and
he reads like an apostle.
But to me he reads like a blend between Paul and...
John, you know, but yeah, I think it's just sort of what you are going to use it for.
That's at least where I would come down on that.
I don't know what you think, Father.
Yeah, we're about to get into sort of the contents, right, of the shepherd.
And I think part of it is sort of based on what it is and what it's about, right?
And super short, unbelievably short.
summary, it's really about how to live a Christian life. If you want the most the most basic
description, right? Like if it was on the shelf at your local lifeway Christian store, it
would be in the Christian living section, right? Like that's the sort of subgenre.
Parallel, which would be like parallel with the dedicate kind of thing. Even more so. And
I mean even more so in the sense that like the
Okay, sort of like an early church order.
This is very, this reads very much like a second century version of the kind of thing
that evangelicals publish a lot of.
This is obviously much better in my mind than those.
I'm not going to, I haven't read all of them, so I can't say any of them, but I did
delete it that direction, right?
In terms of just, you know, how do I live my life as a Christian?
Dealing with very basic ideas of virtue and vice of this kind of thing, right?
And like pursue this, avoid that, right?
Like, here are traps and passions and sinful temptations you can fall into.
Avoid those.
Here are virtues and good things to struggle toward and work on.
Right?
It's very much like that.
That's why if you've read any St. John Cache and everyone should read more St. John
As everyone knows who watches my Twitch stream.
I play Cyclops and I tell people to read St. John Cashin.
That's basically the summary of the stream.
The reason he quotes it so much is because he's very much writing in that same kind of genre.
Right.
And so he in the fifth century sees the second century version of that as being authoritative and a guide.
he's expanding on that and applying it to particularly monastic setting.
things and his own day and that kind of thing. So it is that kind of thing.
Saving nations as epistles or St. Paulic Arps epistle, like to the Philippians and stuff,
is a different genre than that. Right. And I don't think the difference is a difference
in authority. I think it's a difference in sort of what they're talking about, right?
what they're addressing and what they're focusing on.
Right?
The different kind of...
thing. Perfect. Well, you
absolutely answer that's
actually what I was looking
for you answer the question
perfectly as usual. Thank
you, gentlemen. As usual, I
would say as sometimes happens,
but anyway, thanks for calling
Eddie. Yeah, a lot of times I
just go off on an interesting
ramble. Yeah. Yeah. Don't
answer the question so much as
say a bunch of other interesting
things. Yeah. Right. Thanks for
calling. I have some things I
wanted to say. Yes. Yeah.
You're good.
indication to. Yes, exactly.
Propound upon.
Exactly.
Following topic.
So before we jump into the actual content of the shepherd of Hermas,
I just want to give a little as they were quality housekeeping note.
I don't know why we call these housekeeping notes, but this is what people say.
Yeah, a note about our episodes in July.
So there will still be two episodes in July.
And they will be on the second, four Thursdays of the month.
However, they will both be pre-recorded.
And the reason is
that father and I will be traveling me more than him and so we will not be able to be at the
mic on those nights. But what you will get is stuff that we recorded in front of a live audience
at the Reason Parish Life Conference in Springdale, Arkansas where we both were a couple of weeks ago.
So there will be two episodes and they'll each start with a presentation from one of us.
and then there'll be a live Q&A that follows that.
So it was pretty interesting, I thought,
and there were some good comments and questions
from those who were gathered,
and it was a good time.
And I should let you guys know,
just so you have a sense of anticipation for this.
Father Stevens presentation involves mouse habitats.
Mouse habitats.
Yeah.
Let me tell you, I mean, I haven't watched it back,
but just by memory of, as it went on,
I mean, Father Andrews usual was perfectly acceptable,
did he set a job?
I was sterling.
There I say magnificent.
And that could be taken in different ways.
So that is true.
I mean, there's a lot of people called the magnificent in history and various kinds
of reasons.
Yeah.
So, so what is in the shepherd of Hermes?
Stuff.
Zero.
Yeah.
You need to work out those, man.
You need to work out those.
I know.
What is sterling and magnificent? The contents of the shepherd of her.
So, yeah, so in terms of, we mentioned, we just mentioned, with the second caller,
sort of the very broad stroke that it's about living a Christian life.
The sort of major sub themes, we might say, of that,
Turns out things that are really imp...
the size is a certain understanding of the church and you'll see what we mean by that as we get into
the contents, a particular understanding of the church and the idea of repentance, the importance of
of repents. So that said, let us get into the nitty gritty, yeah, as it were. So you heard
a little uh
a little piece, Father Andrew Red, a little piece back to the beginning of the episode. That was already like an hour and a half ago. So I'm sure Father Andrew doesn't even remember it.
Barely.
But so that the beginning of the visions is occasioned by him by Hermas encountering the spirit of Rota once again.
Yeah, I wrote it.
And as you heard, I find it hard to picture this road of being Valerie Bertinelli somehow.
But, wow, there's a good 80s right there.
I still, it's still hard for me to believe that she was the wife.
She's not still anymore.
Or did they, I don't know, of Edie Van Halen.
Okay, that's Valerie Bertinelli.
Isn't that what you just said?
Now, I'll...
I'm just getting old, I guess.
Go ahead. Go ahead.
Keep on keep on keeping on, Father.
Just losing my say, did I get it wrong? Did I say the wrong
Valerie? You said Valley Bernelli. Sound off in the chat.
What did he say? Did he say Valley,
Bernelli the first time I could have sworn that's what it might be?
That's not the Valerie I meant. Anyway.
Okay. Valley, Bert Nelly was on
too close for comfort.
One of us is going insane and I'm not
Rota. Okay. I'm gone.
I indicate me, Chad. Come on. Come on. Yeah.
I would have made a Schneider joke if I was going for Valley.
Bert Nelly. Okay. Okay.
Rota was Valerie.
I'd be unable to move on from this.
I'm caught in a recurse. Valerie Harper.
Valerie Harper, there we go.
see you did say Bernelli earlier and you did. Oh, they're saying you said
Bernelli. I am way off my game, guys. Sam our most frequent caller ever has
confirmed this. That is a second. There are authority. Sam has a secondary
authority at least in the YouTube chat. Yes. I am way off my game. I met
Valley Harper. I've got a Bernelli who's on too close for comfort. What made
Stop gaslighting me, fuck.
And Valerie Bertonelli got a divorce.
Yes.
That's what I was. I felt like Eddie bad Halen way back.
And if she had called herself Valley Burton, Ellie van Halen, I mean, in Van Halen,
I mean, that guy's your fellow Dutchman, right?
I think technically.
Yes.
I don't know that he was dragged deeply of Dutch culture at any point, but,
Eddie or Alex for that matter.
But yeah, they were divorced before she was even on hot and Cleveland like that.
Yeah.
We're going deep into TV land. That's what happened. I folks TV land. Now,
apparently, Eddie Van Halen is only five foot eight. That makes me call into question his
dutchness. Well, he's also deceased. So and Alex, yeah, yeah. And then Alex,
six feet, which is kind of short for a Dutchman. Why are you looking up their heights?
I don't know, because we were talking about them being Dutch. It's not the neat thing I think of.
The first thing I think of anyway, the first thing you hear a person's name and you're like,
I wonder how tall they are.
I mean, being a little crazy one here.
This is one of these digressions that people complain about in the Apple Podcast reviews
father.
So get it together.
Come on.
Okay.
So rolling it back, you see his road again.
I have trouble picturing hers, Valerie Harper.
Here we go.
And of course, as you heard reference in Father Andrew's intro,
He had had certain thoughts about her.
Yeah, which he says.
And I only thought that you would be a good wife.
Yeah, nothing more.
When I saw her, I was sure about the water.
Sure, bro.
Right.
And so that, that, right, is the occasion for
then the first vision happens.
As we mentioned, there are five visions.
the first
what happens and he sees this elderly woman and this elderly woman as he
repents of having had those thoughts he's now a married man married to another
woman as he repents of those rodesian thoughts as it were he sees the old
old woman grow young and become a young bride.
And so the idea here is that in this vision, the old woman represents the church.
And so when the people who make up the church, when they are, the idea here is that when they
are living in a way that is worldly, when they are living in unrepentant sin, the church
which becomes feeble and weak.
Right, and when...
they are repenting of their sins and when they are seeking after virtue, then the church becomes strong
and young and beautiful as the bride of Christ. So this is the beginning of, remember I said a
particular view of the church. This is a... The church here is...
seen as being on one hand, not separable from the actual Christians who make up the church.
Right. So it's not the church is as a kind of institution or the church is abstracted.
right? This is not like the heavenly invisible church in some platonic sense.
as opposed to the actual gathering of humans on this earth.
Right?
This is the church and the people who make it up are united.
And so whether they are repenting or not is affecting the character of the church as a whole.
The church here is a collective entity made up of.
her members. And so it's sort of similar to the way in which Israel is depicted as a woman
in the prophetic visions of the Old Testament. This is another connecting line.
This image gets picked up a lot, especially later Christian literature, the church as a
woman. Yeah. Yeah.
So, and we'll be developing this idea of the church more as we go on through the material.
This is where it's introduced.
The second vision then happens in the same place one year later.
So one year later on the same stretch of road, Hermes encounters the same old woman,
the church and she gives him a book to copy.
She says, here's a book, make a copy of it for the church, and then she takes it back.
Right?
So he doesn't get to keep it.
He just gets the copy.
And the basic theme is a warning about the seriousness of post-baptismal sins.
Yeah.
Now, this is if you've done any reading at all, right, in the Church Fathers, from, say,
the second to the fourth centuries, especially, you know about the various thoughts and opinions
and things concerning post-baptismal sins, right?
So we read, I don't remember which episode it was, but it was a recent episode where we
read a couple of the apostasy passages in Hebrew.
We're going to talk about there being no sacrifice for voluntary sins after baptism.
Right?
And so we know there were people in the church in that era who took that very literally,
like literally thought you could not be forgiven if you sinned after your baptism.
And so you get the practice that became very common in the late third and early fourth century
4th century of postponing that.
And then the fourth century church father sort of pushed back against that.
Yeah.
Right.
And and sort of quashed that idea.
But there was a very little reading.
So a lot of people will based on this vision and some other things later,
the text will say, oh, well, the shepherd of Hermas is one of those sources
that's saying there's no forgiveness for post baptismal sins.
That's why it's hammering this post baptismal sin.
baptismal.
or are so severe. But here's the thing, and Shabbat Herbis is a little weird here on this,
and that it doesn't say you can't repent of post-baptismal sins. It says, you get one chance
to repent of post-baptismal sins. Yeah, which seems odd if you take that to mean
if you send literally twice. Yeah, if you get early, literally. Yeah.
Yeah, that seems super weird if you take it super literally.
Right.
Why not three times?
One, you know, that seems really arbitrary.
God will give you one after you get baptized, but then that's it, right?
Yeah, and so I would argue that that doesn't make sense and that the way we should understand
the one chance, right? The one opportunity to repent is referring to our life on this earth,
post-baptism. The idea
is that post-baptismal sin is very serious, meaning when you're baptized for the forgiveness
of sins, right, that means you're starting a new life and you're going to live a different
way. Your life needs to change radically, right? In the sense that you need to start avoiding
sin and pursuing virtue, right? But by talking about this chance, the chance it's talking
about use your Christian life.
life in this world. This is when you get to repent that there isn't repentance after
death. I think is what this is aimed at. Yeah. You have one chance and that chances
this life. Yes. Sitting after baptism is very serious and so you need to repent of it
in this life, right? I think that's really the thrust of what it's aimed at, right? And
that reading makes much more sense than the other one.
So then the third vision.
develops a little more and the imagery of the third vision is going to get expanded on in a huge way.
Yeah, this portion of the later text is going to return to this. This is one of the really striking parts of the text, I think, is this image.
And this is another image of the church. So this is expanding on the view of the church. And this is the church is a tower that is being built.
Yeah.
Okay.
And...
It's being built from stones,
being built by angels, which is how cool.
Yeah.
And there's even this explanation in there
that like that the angels have care for the,
not just care for, but like help to develop the creation.
Yeah.
And they are as they're building with these stones,
they are selecting stones.
So they get a stone, right?
And they bring it over and they see if it fits.
Right? And there are stones that fit well, and there are stones that don't that get discarded.
Now this is going to get returned to. But the idea obviously is that the stones are human beings.
And we'll come back to this where this image gets really fully developed. But
this is obviously picking up on language like from St. Paul,
right where the church is built on the foundation of the
and the apostles at Christ's the chief quarterstone,
and then it gets built upon, right?
Or the imagery of the new Jerusalem in revelation
with the jams and stones that are the apostles.
Right?
So this is that same kind of idea.
I will come back to this, right?
this idea of the church as a tower built out of
human stones is important. And again, you can see that for the shepherd of
Hermes, there's not a distinction between the church as such, the church
capital C and the collection of actual humans, right? Particular humans in a
particular place at a particular time, who are part of a particular community
celebrating the sacraments, etc. Those are not sort of two different things.
the fourth vision this is the this is the cool
one. This is the one that the Lord of the Lord of the Spirit's audience turns out for.
So the fourth vision he sees the great beast, not Jonathan Pazzo,
despite what the internet might tell you. I mean, you are born on the number of the beast. It is
clear that you are the beast. Yes. Yes. If either Pazzo or I is the beast, if it's down to the two of us,
That's it.
definitely me. So the Great Beast, which is a hundred foot long whale, Leviathitos,
right? Like so think like Leviathan, right? Like whale from Jonah, right? A hundred foot long
that breathes a swarm of locusts.
Oh yeah, the swarm of locusts is on fire.
You
I mean, that's pretty, pretty metal.
Yes, it's like the sharks with lasers on their heads, right?
Yes, I mean, this is, this is the kind of thing that would be in a movie you would like
to watch.
Yes, yes.
100 foot long whale breathing out a swarm of locusts on that is on fire, flaming locusts.
And the beast is four colors.
Like his sections are four colors. The first one is black, first part is black.
The second part is red, but it doesn't say red in the text. It says,
the color of blood and fire because we want to make it more metal, right? Yeah.
Yeah. And then gold and then white.
And in the explanation of the vision, the four colors are four periods of history.
The black
represents this world, this sinful world. The color of blood and fire represents the coming
tribulation, great tribulation that is coming. The gold represents the faithful who are refined,
let gold by the fire of the great tribulation, and the white represents the life of the world to come.
and by the
way also this is you know Lord of Spirits fan service. You know the word that's
translated as whale okay is Kitos which is the word that is used in the Greek
version of the book of Jonah for the sea monster. So this is very
Leviathanic kind of you know imagery here. You shouldn't be thinking in your
had like a humpback whale, you know that's that I mean
Since when do you see humpback whales breathing flaming locusts?
Right?
Right.
But the viathons are the other hand.
They always breathe.
Yeah, that's all the time.
Yeah.
This isn't like, yeah, a humpback, like George and Gracie, you know, doing whale songs
to ward off an alien probe.
Which is, I think that one is tied for, yeah, that one is definitely tied for my favorite
Star Trek Phil.
along with Star Trek 6, undiscovered country.
Obviously, Wrath of Khan is the greatest Star Trek film ever made.
Like, on these days, I'm going to get...
What is self-attesting?
When Christmas comes around, I am going to get a wreath
and have Ricardo Montabon's face put in the middle of it.
I can hang from the front of the studio, so I will have the wreath of Khan
and just see if anybody gets it.
Yeah
So, man, just drew the energy right down.
Anyway.
So, yeah, four always has a special place in my heart,
because it was the first one I saw in a movie theater.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And afterwards, we went to a McDonald's and I ate my first big Mac.
Maybe as to that, I had only had hamburgers and cheeseburgers.
Hmm.
But that...
day at nine years old, I ate my first big Mac. That day I became a man. Anyway, so fifth vision.
This is as we said, there's sort of some nesting here because the fifth vision, the shepherd appears
and the shepherd identifies himself as the angel of repentance.
And he has pale white skin.
So he's got apparently and has with him the rod of correction.
So that kind of repentance, right?
Discipline going on.
And so the shepherd is going to be, I mean, he's not really a psychopomp because they kind
of don't go on a journey per se.
Right.
It's more like some of the angelic beings who appear to...
profits, right, during their visions and like explain things or like the archangel Gabriel
explaining things to Daniel, right, that he sees in visions.
So then the rest of the text is going to be the 12 commandments, which bear no direct relationship
to the ten commandments by the
other say you thought the
you
And then the 10 parables.
So the 12 commandments, commandment number one, is to fear the one true God who created
all things.
And fear of God here is defined not as being afraid of God, but as the way you demonstrate
fear of God is by exercising self-control.
You
Because you have fear and reverence in awe toward God, you try to avoid sin, right?
And do good and please God.
Right.
Commandment two is to become like a child.
And this is not just become childish.
Sorry.
internet, you have not arrived at Christian virtue. It used to become like a
child in particular sense. It's really talking about becoming innocent. The way a
child is innocent. Because the two ways that's kind of developed is number one
that you be innocent in that you speak evil of no one. You don't you don't
slander anyone. You don't speak evil things about people. And then number two,
you give freely to every
want to need. So you give alms, right? The idea here being that an innocent person shares
and an innocent person speaks only good things. If you know children, you know that's not
what they're like, but this, you get the idea here. Don't be like an actual child, be
actual child be like a hypothetical innocent child.
Commandment three.
is to love the truth and to hate falsehood.
And this is not just in the sense of what you believe or something,
but in terms of how you act,
right, that you love
seeking the truth and speaking the truth,
right, you love honesty,
and you hate
treachery, dissembling, lying,
right, falsehood of any kind, right?
and love here means pursue.
and hate means avoid, detest, run from, keep far from you.
Right.
Commandment 4 is to maintain sexual purity, right, to avoid sexual immorality.
But, but if you actually read this section,
there's important, important, provisos we have to put here, because
especially when we're talking about some of these ancient texts,
Christian and Christian Ajay.
Right? By Christian Jason. I mean like stuff from Nostics and stuff.
People make an assumption that maintain sexual purity means well number one, people assume it means be celibate, which it definitely does not here.
Right? Because Hermes is a married man.
Right. Right. Right. It's got to have kids and that scene is a good thing in the text.
That scene is a blessing from God.
uh or they uh
interpreted in a very sort of strict and harsh way.
But for example, part of what is commanded in this section is that if a man's wife commits
adultery but she is honestly repentant, he should receive her back.
How is that maintaining sexual purity you might ask?
Some people would interpret that as being the opposite.
That forgiving her would be the opposite of maintaining sexual purity.
Right?
But no, it's seen as maintaining sexual purity because, remember what St. Paul said,
the marriage bed is wholly an undefiled.
Yeah.
And so preserving that marriage bed, it being purified again through forgiveness,
is better than divorce, even though divorce was permitted for adultery.
Because if you break that marital bond, it can't be holy or pure anymore.
It's broken.
Right.
It's not there.
So, this is a very robust view of sexual purity that incorporates marriage having children,
family life.
Right.
And it's talking about maintaining sexual purity in not violating the purity of the marital
relationship, for example, by committing adultery yourself.
Right.
Yeah, or doing anything else that would break that bond.
Fifth commandment, avoid anger and seek patience.
So anger and patience are the two polls here, right?
Like truth and falsehood, anger and patience, which is kind of interesting, right?
Being long suffering in biblical terminology, having a long nose.
and we talked about that recently.
show. I don't think that's one of my favorite odd biblical idioms. So in Hebrew, a common
Hebrew idiom for getting angry is that your nose is hot. Yeah. And if you think about it,
that's the idea that you're like breathing through your nose. Right? So your nose is
heating up. And so a related idiom for someone who is very patient and has a long fuse is
that they have.
a long nose. So there are these texts in the Hebrew Old Testament Hebrew Bible that talk about
God having a long nose and you're like, what? But that's what's referring to. It's usually translated
as him being long suffering, right? Him being. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
And so I mean, that seems kind of obvious. But one of the interesting things is the way which
anger is described in this commandment is that anger
is a spirit. It's like the idea of anger is a passion that enters into a person and takes control
of them. Anger is almost like a demon possessing a person. I mean, you know, yeah, right? That's
kind of how it works, right? Yeah. Yeah. But the danger here is it actually talks about that spirit
of anger if you let it take root and come
into you and dwell in you, it displaces the Holy Spirit. Who dwells in you?
Yeah. And I think there's a sort of deliberate analogy here to what happens with Saul in the old
Testament, King Saul, not Saul of Tarsus. Right? Where I remember, he has the Holy Spirit, the
Holy Spirit departs at one point and an unclean spirit comes, and he has this sort of murderous
rage toward David. Yeah. It's the same kind of thing. Right? Whereas patience is one of the
fruits of the Spirit.
Right, right.
And so it's kind of this idea and command of heart.
We see this in the shepherd of Hermes of you're going to participate in something, right.
There's going to be some spirit at work in you.
It needs to be the Holy Spirit, not a spirit like anger, right.
Sixth commandment.
Some of you will be surprised to learn where this comes from.
person has two angels.
other shoulders. What is the angel of righteousness and what is the angel of
iniquity? I mean it's just like in the cartoons. And these angels send thoughts
into your head. It's just like in the cartoons. The guide you in one direction or
the other. Yeah. And you need to choose which one you're going to follow.
Uh...
Claremont 7.
fear God not the devil. Yeah, I mean does does that mean it definitely can't
mean like be afraid of God like quaking in your boots and not quaking in your
boots about the devil. So I mean is this fear God in the sense of reverence like
reverence for God and reverence for the devil? Well it's talking about that in
terms of behavior.
in terms of what you do. It's not talking about an attitude or how you think about God or how you think about the devil.
So in this context, fearing the devil means the devil is sort of being viewed here as the prince of this world.
Hmm. Okay. Right. And so it's like, are you going to be afraid of what can happen to you in this world?
The devil is very much talked about in the shepherd of Hermes the way Satan has talked about in
Job. Okay. So he's kind of on
a leash from God, but you know, he
can hurt you. He could do these
different things to you in this
world. He could take things away
from you. He could destroy your
crops, your wealth, your family,
your right. Like you could do all
those things. And you can turn
over hand over the reins to him.
Right. And so if you're afraid of
that, if you're biggest fear in
life, if you're biggest concern in
life is not
losing those things that you have in this life, you're going to act in certain ways, right?
And not good ways, in sinful ways. Whereas if the one you fear is God, if what you're afraid of is
you know, standing before the day of judgment and being disqualified, right? Then you're going to
to live your life. That's your deepest concern.
then you're going to, is God's view of you, then you're going to live your life in a certain way
and do certain things and those are going to be good things, right? And so that's what it's getting at
when it's talking about fearing God and not fearing the devil is what is your guiding concern? What do you
think is the worst thing that could happen to you? That you're going to work really hard to avoid?
right? Is it something in this way?
world or is it related to God's ultimate judgment of you in your life?
Yeah.
Commandment 10, it's probably the best news for me out of all these commandments.
And that is that you should avoid grief and be joyful.
Thank you.
Thank you, father.
So our, the constant giggling, see, guys, that's...
It's a form of repentance.
That's why.
But now, avoid grief sounds weird.
Right?
And in the text here, it talks about grief crushing the Holy Spirit.
That's the language it uses.
Where in joyfulness is pleasing to God.
Yeah, I mean, there's a sense of quenching the spe-
right? Yeah, yeah. This is crushing. Right. Oh, gee. So like I crushed your head, but the the idea
here, because you're like grief. And when he's talking about grief, he's talking about grief. He's
talking about mourning losses in this life. It's not being sad, including being sad over losing people
for you.
And animals you love in all this.
Hmm, right?
He's saying that's bad.
Now, he's not saying you're not allowed to grieve at all, right?
Like, you shouldn't be sad at all when somebody you love passes away, right?
That's not what he's saying.
But he's talking about how if you just dwell in that grief,
if you let grief over losing things in this life,
you could also think about not just losing people,
but losing a job, losing an opportunity,
losing a dream.
that you had when you were younger, that maybe isn't going to ever come true, right?
Gre... all those kinds of grief. If you live in that and you dwell in that and it
becomes despair and despondency, right? At these kind of things. That's what he's
saying will crush the Holy Spirit, right? That's what he's saying is the
problem. What he's opposing to that is joy, joy that comes from God.
Right? And that joy that comes from God is that pleases God, right, is joy even in the
face of suffering and those things. Right? Yeah. And we can have that joy if for Christians
because we know that whatever we lost, whatever loss we experience in this life, if it's
someone we loved, it's not permanent, right? If it's a job or a dream or any of those
other, what this life isn't forever, right? We could put this life into folk into a different
Thank you.
context, a different focus, right? Yeah, and like
probably for at least for the most of us who are living in the relatively comfortable
Western world, especially the United States, probably the
for a lot of us especially if you don't have any like big health problems with something like that.
I mean some of the biggest suffering you might have in your life is related to relationships
and so much of that comes. I like you said it was interesting you said
you know you maybe had this dream of your youth whatever things didn't quite work out the way
you wanted them to, which I think is kind of all of us on some level, probably once you
get to a certain age, I'm living the dream, but I know you are. I know you are. You know,
sorry, you know, I'm probably bumming out the Zoomers right now, but, um, but I think,
you know, I'm dead ex. So I don't know how many dreams I ever had. We were, we were raised
like, forget it, forget it. We were relegated. We were born. The boomers mortgage, everything,
Sorry, you know, you...
You get nothing.
But I think also that the sense of in the life of the age to come that a lot of the broken
relationships we have in this life that I think a lot of people will, God willing, if
they're repentant in this life, look at each other and go, oh, I'm sorry, you know, that
there's so many kinds of ways that we just don't understand each other now.
And so as a result, our relationships never go in the direction we want them to go.
and yet we'll understand much better because very...
applicable for us in our time. Yeah. Yeah. And another point that's made here is that when you
allow yourself to remain in that place of grief and it becomes despair and despondency,
that grief, the pain, never gets healed. Right. It's just continuous and constant. Whereas,
the showroom of herstals is that it's when we're living in that joy.
that comes from God that comes from the Holy Spirit, that is a fruit of the Spirit, again,
when we're living in that joy, that joy is what heals the pain
that brought about the grief in the first place.
Yeah. Right. Yep. And that's as free from it.
So then commandment 11 is to discern the prophets.
Right. Remember the shoulder.
angels, right? Well, there's people showing up, presenting
themselves as prophets and leaders in the church. And you need
to be discerning in terms of which ones you follow, which ones
you believe, which ones you hear out, right? And he gives
very concrete things, right? If you, someone who you should
follow is going to manifest the kind of character we saw in
the other commandments. Right?
in terms of speaking the truth,
in terms of being patient,
in terms of being joyful, right?
These kind of things,
whereas,
and here tellingly,
the biggest indicator of the false prophet is,
he comes asking for money.
Not that there's anyone like that at all.
I mean, this is one of the things
that shows up in the Diva Ki as well as like,
yeah,
no false prophet,
if he's busy.
He's greed trying to, you know, put the shake down on you.
Yeah, yeah.
Shows of asking for money, but also the opposite, right,
is deceitful as treasures, all of these things.
And there's actually an interesting reference here.
It talks about, it gives an example
when it's talking about the false prophets, the bad guys, right?
Of someone who tries to insert themselves
among the presbyters.
Mm.
Right?
So there's some kind of wandering.
religious figure, and they try to become one of the priests, right? One of the
presbyters in a particular church. And the reason it's interesting is that as we
established, this is being written somewhere in the 140s and somewhere in the
140s, a fellow named Marcian who you may have heard of, showed up in Rome.
and pretty much tried to insert himself among the pressmenors.
So this
maybe a kind of without naming him reference to Marcy and as what a bad guy looks like, right?
In terms of false prophets.
Marcy, of course, is the fellow who rejected the entire Old Testament.
Yeah. So then Commandment 12, the 12th and Final Commandment here is about
thoughts that we should remove evil thoughts from our minds, like not let them take root and
develop into things and
remove the passions, but interestingly it says to replace them with good desires and
Why is that interesting? Well, if you're familiar at all with Greek philosophy. It just about any of its forms
You know that desire was not considered a good thing
right desire itself yeah you know that
that the goal is not to desire.
Right.
Not to desire, or at least not to yield to desires of any kind.
Desires desires desires the source of all suffering, you know, all that stuff.
And is and is not good.
And so the idea that there are good desires, right, is is one of the one of the truly
Christian elements right of the Shepard of Herbis.
This isn't just giving you, and this is the commandments. This isn't just giving you kind of virtue morals, right?
Through a somewhat Christianized lens.
This is a uniquely Christian outlook that there are good desires, right? And part of this is because
the scripture is talking about God-desiring things.
Yeah, right, right. Which is gobbledygook from the perspective of most Greek philosophy.
How could God who is himself?
the highest good desire anything. Right. And then you get lines like in the Psalms, you
know, one thing I've I desire to dwell on the house of the Lord forever, you know, that kind
of stuff. Yeah. Yeah. And so that means there have to be good desires. Ed, that's an example
of the Father Andrew just gave, right? Desiring to please God. Desiring to do good. Desiring
to like herb us have a family to be married and have children.
Right.
all of these desires are good desires. So this way, you're not called to replace evil thoughts
and desires with a kind of stoicism or indifference, right? But with good desires, actively pursuing
Good. Right. And so desire itself is not bad. So this brings us.
to the final section, the 10 parables.
Okay.
Parable one.
And these are all parables in the sense of like Christ parables.
And it's the same word in the Greek.
It's parable-bling, right?
So where we get the English word parable.
Yeah.
So the first parable is about a stranger who is traveling in a foreign land.
So a straight
Andrew's traveling in a foreign land doesn't go and buy property in the foreign land.
He doesn't lay down stakes.
He doesn't settle there because he's planning on returning to his homeland.
And so whatever business he does when he's in a foreign land, he's doing it with the
purpose of driving some benefit from it back home.
And so the idea here is that Christians are, and this is picking up on a theme for
from St. Peter as a Pissill, that Christians are strangers in a foreign land in this world.
And so we don't lay down stakes and try to acquire things in this world. The things we do
in this world, we do with an eye toward when we return to our homeland.
Yeah. Right. At the Tower of departure of this life in the life of the world to come.
The second parable is about an elm tree and a vine.
And the vine grows up around the elm tree,
sort of uses the elm tree to support itself, right?
And then bears fruit.
And so this is explained as being a parable about the wealthy and the poor, right?
Those who are in the world and those who devote the borough
devote their lives to prayer. So the wealthy person, the person living in the world doing business in the world
That person is like the Elm tree
He is solid and he grows himself, but he does not himself bear a lot of fruit
Elm trees don't bear fruit, but the vine the vine cannot support itself the vine needs to be supported
and then what supported the vine is able to...
to bear a lot of fruit. And so there is this symbiotic relationship between the tree, the
tree of the vine. And it's about the same kind of symbiotic relationship should exist within
the church between the wealthy and the poor, those who are active in the world, those who
devote themselves to prayer. And this is going to end up, you can see how this develops
into our understanding of the relationship between Christians who live in the world and
and monastic.
right within the church, right? The monastics are able to devote themselves to prayer because
they aren't required to live in the world and take care of all of those things, but the people
who are living in all of those worlds and doing all those things can support the monastics
to enable them to be able to do that.
Which I mean, this is just a pattern set up with the Levites in the Old Testament.
Yeah, yeah.
Third parable.
Talks about how when you go out among the trees in the winter, you can't tell in the
dead of winter which ones are dead and which ones are alive.
You have to wait until the spring.
And when the spring comes, the trees that are alive, bud and blossom, and those that are
dead do not.
And so this parable is about how in this world, in this time,
Right? When we look at people, we can't necessarily tell who's spiritually dead and who's spiritually alive.
But at the judgment, the judgment of Christ, that gets revealed.
Right? Then the fruit are revealed.
There's going to be a number of these tree analogies.
So get ready for that.
The next, the next parallel parable for is developing on this again.
So the same imagery.
So in the fourth one is specifically about
Bye bye.
willotries. I am no dendrologist. So I don't know the details of this, but for purposes of this
parable in the shepherd of Hermes, apparently willotries, some of them keep their leaves in the winter
and some of them don't. We'll just go with it. Yeah, so for purposes of this, we'll say that's the case.
Yeah, which that is what I'm talking about which means so it's talking
particular kind of tree where it's not clear cut whether it's deciduous or evergreen.
Right.
It's somewhere in between.
Some of them drop leaves and some don't in the winter.
And so this image then is talking about when hardships and difficulties come in this
life, right?
Some people who have acquired virtue, when hardship comes, those virtues sort of quickly
fall away, right?
the patients they may have.
develop to the joy, right? All of those fruits of the spirit that they may have developed.
When the hard times come, it kind of all falls away. There are other people who are able
to endure those hard times and continue to bear fruit, even during the difficult times.
And of course, you're called to be the latter, not the former. Parable five, then, and
This one is going to be familiar to readers of the Bible.
There is a...
There's a master who owns a vineyard.
And he leases it out to a tenant.
And the tenant, huh?
I said, I feel like I've heard this somewhere before.
Yeah, although there's a little variation here, right?
So the tenant, he works the vineyard.
He works it very diligently.
And then when the harvest comes, he receives a reward, right?
From the master of the vineyard.
And here...
The master who owns the vineyard is God. The tenant is a person identified as the son of God,
and if he works diligently in the garden, then he acquires a reward from God at the end of the day.
I think it's pretty clear what that means, but we're going to come back to this,
this because turns out this ends up being supercultruversial in modern
it's got
scholarship. Okay, nowhere else, but in modern scholarship. So the third half we're going to come back to this fifth parable.
Um, parable six, two shepherds, there are two shepherds. One is the angel of discipline.
And one is the angel of luxury. Okay. So there are, and people follow one or the other.
to follow the Angel of Discipline just follow.
the angel of discipline. Those who follow the angel of luxury end up getting turned over later
to the angel of discipline who disciplines them far more severely.
Might as well just go if we're disciplined to start. See, bingo!
So it's pretty clear what this is what this is stating. There are people who pursue a disciplined
the way
of life. And so continued to have a discipline as a way of life. There are those who yield
and try to yield to luxury and the pleasures of the world. They end up getting disciplined.
But that discipline ends up being often far harsher when they have to be brought back into line
that it would have been if they had just been disciplined about things the whole time.
Yeah, they parable seven
gives us a dramatic example of exactly what kind of discipline we're talking about
with those who pursued luxury because he has in the parable the age of discipline comes
for Hermes and his family.
So the idea here is this is the spiritual understanding we mentioned way back at the beginning
that Hermes had experienced this loss of his business and his wealth.
And this is sort of his spiritual understanding of it.
the reason this happened.
all of this was him being turned over to the angel of discipline. That in his
wealth, in his happiness over his family of having all of these good things of the
world, he had become lax. He had become prone to sin. And he wasn't living in a
discipline to weigh in a Christian way. And so these hardships all came upon him
through an angel from God, right?
In his underst-
standing in order to bring him back into discipline, bring him back into line for his repentance.
And that him patiently enduring those hardships would purify him and straighten him out from
the sins that he had fallen into when he was living in a more luxurious way.
So he receives temporal physical heart.
chips as being repentance and purification. And so they end up being for his benefit.
Eighth parable.
Big crowd of people bringing willow branches, sheaves of willow branches,
more willow trees, to an angel. And the angel is sorting through the willow branches.
And some of them are green. And some of them are withered. And some of them are rotten.
So in this parable, when it's explained, the branches are the laws of God or commandments
of God.
And so the sheaves of branches that are being brought by the people, this represents
at the judgment, right?
We have all received these commandments.
The green ones are the ones that we have kept, right, and followed, so they're a lot.
and bearing fruit, right? The withered ones are the ones that we've sort of kept half
heartedly or abividedly, or maybe sometimes and maybe not, and then the rotten ones are
just the ones that we haven't kept. Right? And so all of that is sort of sorted through
at the judgment. And now we get to parable nine. We're almost there.
books. Parables eight nine are 40% of the text of the Shepherd of Hermas. And most of that
is parable nine. And so we're not going to go into, we're not going to spend 40% of the
episode on parable nine, if you started to get scared right there. I don't father Andrew
He never sleep again.
This episode would be like five hours.
as long. But so parable nine, here's the short version, there are 12 mountains. And those 12 mountains
represent 12 types of people, 12 types of Christians people in particular, 12 types of Christians,
12 types of people in the church. And the mountain range then is a range of people.
On one end, you have the righteous.
You have people and bishops are included in this.
You have people who have totally devoted, the idea of being,
people have totally devoted their life to following Christ
and keeping his commandments.
That's sort of one end.
And then on the far end, you have apostates and blasphemers.
And then you have a whole range of people in between.
Right those two
And so once again, angels are building a tower.
The tower is the church.
This is what we said we were going to expand on this.
Yeah.
Earlier, this is the big expansion.
There are six angels building the tower.
And it says in the text that these six angels
represent the six lower ranks of angels
who oversee the earth, the events on earth and people.
Okay.
meaning the higher ranks are concerned with God himself, right? And they're the highest ranks the highest part of heaven.
This corresponds by the way to in terms of there being six lower orders and what they do to St. Dionysius, the area of the guise celestial hierarchy.
Yeah, yeah, so if you want one more little piece of argument for those of you out there
making the argument that
that it is the St. Dionysius of the first century Athens.
This is written in the 140s.
So if it's referencing that,
there's another little piece of evidence for you.
You have to put pseudo on front of his name.
You just don't.
Put Saint on his name, that's what I'm saying.
We have a relic of St. Dionysius, the area apogite,
at what you referred to as my Southern mega church
that I now attend.
Oh, there you go.
All saying to...
in Raleigh. So come on down if you guys want to venerate St. Dinesias everybody.
Which campus are we're about to become multi actually we've been multi-site for what now just
kitty. That the Durham campus right. I like to say to people that all scenes in Raleigh right now
is very pregnant and probably with triplets. So yeah. There we go. Yeah. Is that just because
of the egg.
organized whaling that comes out of the, are you throwing shade at the chancers? Is that what?
No, no, no. The chancers are lovely. They do an excellent job. No, no, it's the, uh,
the fact that we need to sprout multiple missions, which we're working on. We're, we're getting there.
Yeah. Um, so there's these 12 mountains, the angels, there's rocks that are getting
and hewn out of the different mountains.
So if the mountains are types, the rocks are actual, right?
Christian.
those rocks then get sort of tested, right? And Wade and checked out, and they have to be
clothed in virtue. And there's a little, there's a little bit of a play on words here with dressing
stone when we talk about clothed in virtue. And dressing stone is in preparing it to be, right,
put into a stonework and this isn't the tower.
In order to touch the tower, the stone has to be clothed in virtue.
That's the idea.
And so they're sorted and they're being put into the tower.
And the text interprets the sorting, not as the last judgment.
Right? The process that the angels are doing is not about the last judgment,
but is about church discipline.
So the idea is that part of what's going on within the church is church
discipline with the intent of preparing all of these stones to become part of the tower.
Yeah, I mean, there's a thing like in the beginning of the text, where he first sees the tower,
and then he asks, Rota about what it all means.
There's a bit in there about certain stones being thrown away, but not very far.
And it's the sense of like they still need to be prepared a little bit more, you know,
and maybe they could be incorporated into the tower, essentially if they repent, because
they represent Pete Wright.
Yeah, right. And so, um,
I'm sure it's just what happens. The tower is being built on an ancient rock,
which is the Son of God.
Right. So it's being built on the rock that is Christ, right?
So you can see all the biblical imagery that's being picked up on here,
even though it's being remixed a little.
Um,
and then once the tower is finished,
so this would be at the judgment.
But the tower is finished. The tower...
is completely seamless, not only in terms of the stones that make up the tower, so you have perfect unity,
right, of the church, once this process is done, that's what's being worked toward,
but it is also seamlessly united with the rock on which it is built, with Christ himself.
So the church is perfectly one and perfectly one with Christ.
Yeah, there's a lot of emphasis on the seamlessness of the stones as they're put together,
which is interesting. Yeah.
Yeah.
So the, you can say both that the people are part of the church, right?
And that they're becoming part of the church, right?
They are being prepared for the church through this process.
So what this means that is that, and we're going to come back to this in the third
which we'll get to shortly, I promise.
Stay awake, Father.
Um, yeah.
Is that, uh, in one way,
it's preparation to be to be part of the church, right?
Ultimately being found to be part of the church is what it means to be saved in a certain way.
Yeah, right. Here, here in the text.
Um,
and then the 10th and final parable, Hermes gets
commanded to bring the contents of all, meaning the book we're reading when we read the
shepherd, right? The contents of all these visions, right, to the church. And this reemphasis
that everything that's been talked about in the text is doable. Right? This is not beyond
the Christian who is indwelt by the Holy Spirit, et cetera, et cetera. Yeah. It's not something
to do. There's a big emphasis. I went back and reread like I couldn't, I didn't have enough
time to read the
text because it's like about a hundred pages in most of the editions. But I read the beginning,
you know, just try to kind of re-familiarize myself with it. And there's often the sense of,
like there's one point, for instance, when Hermes asks, Roda, like she says, comes it down with me.
And so he goes to sit on the right. She's like, no, you can't sit on the right. You have to sit on
the left. And he's like, why? What's the deal? And she says, those on the right are basically those
who are perfected.
And you're not there yet buddy.
you can sit but it has to be on the left for now.
Maybe you'll get to the right at some point.
And I mean, this is really striking because it's a sense
of, it's the sense of that repentance is possible,
that repentance is fruitful, you know,
that it does something, right?
And so yeah, this sense of things are doable,
like, like, look, just keep moving,
you're not there yet, but you can do this.
You know, that's one of the,
the emphases that I noticed as I was re-reading it this afternoon.
Yeah.
So that's the contents.
And so when we return for half number three, why does everybody think there are problems
with the show?
Hermes.
Why is the Shepherd of Hermes so explosively scary?
So yes.
Alright, we're going to take our second and final break and we'll be right back with the
third half of this episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
other injuries.
And Amen, Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
Take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
A royal life set aside or a crown transformed into something brighter.
Elizabeth, Princess, Abbas, Saint, a br-
And new children's picture book invites readers into a world where kindness sparkles brighter than jewels and small acts of love ripple into eternity.
Walk beside a princess who chooses humility over splendor, finds joy in giving and who turns ordinary moments into something luminous reminding us that true beauty is not worn but lived.
Elizabeth Princess Abyss Saint is available now in our bookstore at store.AncientFaith.com
Again!
that is store.angiefefe.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, we're back.
You know, that might be, I don't know if I'm remembering.
correctly, but that might be the first children's book that's been advertised here on the
Lotus Prius podcast.
Am I remembering what do you think, Father?
I don't know.
I don't pay attention during the commercial.
Yeah, it's it's it.
Well, this one actually does have a connection to us.
Believe it or not, Father, about St. Elizabeth the new martyr because the author of it is
one of our professors from our common alma mater, Dr. Mary Ford.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Like, is there is there some kind of ancient faith plus where people could pay a couple
bucks a month and not have to listen to the commercials?
Is that coming soon?
I will talk to the marketing team.
Yeah, because I know, I know you and your executive office, you sit there just thinking,
how can I monetize these people?
It's absolutely the case.
I mean, it's the reason that I that I drive a Bentley to work every day.
It's true.
Yep. Which I alternate with the Hummer that I also own. You know, yeah, yeah. Anyway,
well, we're back and we just went through the contents kind of, I mean, again, like I said,
it's like a hundred pages of text depending on which edition you're looking at. So it was kind of
a wild whirlwind tour through the contents of the Shepherd of Hermes. And I recommend,
I do recommend people read the book actually.
Read the text.
I-
I think that we weren't doing this instead of you reading it.
We were doing it.
No, no.
Hopefully you could read it productively.
Yeah.
And that just be like, what?
That's weird.
Right.
Yeah.
I mean, it's really way more approachable than you might think.
I think.
So, and it's okay to read a text and like, I don't know what half this means, but half of
it was pretty cool.
Like, that's the beginning of understanding right there.
You know, that's, that's fine.
So yeah, we just went through the contents.
And now we're going to talk about, you know, how to understand this and what some of the objections that people have to this text are because I think, I think sometimes when particularly our Protestant friends want to dismiss text from the early church, this is one of the ones that they go to the most and say, well, that's weird and uncannotical and heretical and whatever and why are you bothering with any of this stuff, you know, that could harm you, you know, it's dangerous.
dangerous. So let's talk about it. Yeah. Well, and also just so part of part of why
I wanted to devote a whole half of a show to
do what we're about to talk about is I think this goes beyond the shepherd of Hermes. I think you
see similar problems with other early Christian texts and writings of the church fathers where
some of
a weird scholarly stuff that they do with the shepherd of Hermes is the same kind of stuff
they do with other things.
So this can be kind of a sort of test case, right?
A way we can approach some of these overall errors and approach and methodology by using
her, or the shepherd as an example.
There you go smuggling in larger issues, Father Stephen.
What's the matter with you?
Yes.
I am uniting the universal in the particular whether you like it or not.
I'm sorry.
There's no rain begun.
So, yeah, so from a, in terms of, shall we say criticism or negative or unhelpful approaches
to the shepherd of Hermes, we can talk about from a Protestant perspective, shepherd
of Hermes not super popular among Protestants.
Yeah, I mean it's a good day.
Yeah. And that's for a reason is there are a couple of reasons why it's problematic
from a Protestant perspective. Right. The first one is that good old bug bear works righteousness.
You mean something like repent for the kingdom of heaven as it hand? Oh, well,
So this seems to be conditioning yourself.
on things like repentance and pursuing virtue and doing good works. Right? Like says in the Bible.
Well, hey now now!
Ha ha ha!
Ha ha ha ha!
Right, um, yeah, and um,
so it depends upon what sort of Protestant you are.
in part, right? Indeed.
And, and, and that kind of thing, how big of a bug bear works right as this is to you, right?
Because the perspective here is, frankly, again, one you get in Scripture, which is that at no point
does the shepherd of Hermit, the shepherd of Hermit doesn't even really talk about what we might
today
English, but you can catch that right, getting saved, right? It's not talking about getting
things. It's not about the initial thing. It's not it's written by and to baptized people.
Yeah. And there's all these kind of, you know, when when Hermes is being addressed by
Roda or whatever spirit of speaking to him, they occasionally will even call him this righteous man
or whatever. Right. Right. So this is an intra, right? Church document. It's about how you live
As a Christian, it's not happening.
about how you become a Christian,
it's not about how you first believe in Christ, right?
So none of the works in here are about,
quote unquote, earning salvation, right?
Or justification the way it's talked about
in Protestant circles, right?
This is for people who are in,
have the baptizer in the church,
our Christians are leading a Christian life,
how do you do that?
Right? That's the whole context, right?
And so regardless of what you think
about how that happens.
happens. Shepard Herbys isn't really talking about that. The Shepard Herbys is talking
about, okay, now that you're here, how do you live as a Christian? Yeah. Which, that's
the question that absorbs more of your life, I think. Yeah. Well, yeah, there's plenty
of that in the New Testament. Yeah, yeah, right, right. Like the second half of most of St.
Paul's epistles, right? That's the second part after the therefore, where he gives
exhortations to virtue and this kind of thing and to repentance.
sin, right? And fleek for sin. So it's very much a keeping with that, right? So that really
shouldn't if you contextualize it properly, except for some, I mean, there are some...
Oh, it's not even extreme. If you're a, if you're a one saved, always saved person,
you're going to have a problem with this because there is firmly the idea that shepherd of
of Hermes that you could disqualify yourself from salvation.
Yeah, through unrepentance.
it. Yeah. And that's in the tower image, especially. Yeah. So let's hear it like a one saved
all as a person, right? Like I think even before a process perspective, you could accept
this, right? And maybe there's even a work around there. So I don't think there should
be just a huge just, you know, this is clearly not pallaging, right? Like. And the other
thing, of course, is, as you might expect, is that from a process perspective, Schubert
of her must tends to have to.
too high a view of the church from most Protestant perspectives.
In that, it sees being a member of the church, and even to that extent being a Christian,
right, as something that is achieved, something that comes at the end of life, at maturity
or perfection, right, rather than as being a status that is sort of communicated at the
beginning.
status that is just granted at the beginning of, as the beginning of salvation. Right. So
parenthesis about deny that there are things like sanctification and stuff, right? That
there is a Christian life and all of that. But they want that status to be granted at the
beginning, not what comes at the end. Right. And in the shepherd of Hermas, that's very
clearly something that comes at the end.
But here's the thing
All of that imagery
Both about the Christian life and the stuff about the church
It's all coming directly out of the the Bible. It's all coming directly out of the scriptures
Yeah, right we talked about St Paul using the image of the church being built
Upon the foundation of Christ right and the apostles and the prophets right we we talked about that imagery
Right?
That kind of imagery of the church, the church being built up is in the New Testament, right?
So you may not like the implications, but I mean, it's just sort of developing biblical
imagery.
That's true.
The church that's true of works in Christian living as we've talked about.
The whole bearing fruit is like a major theme in Christ preaching, not just in, right,
say Paul's epistles itself.
the vine bearing fruit, all of this is just directly, you know, a tree by all of this is coming from
the New Testament, not just the scriptures, but the New Testament.
So it seems really difficult to dismiss it out of hand for those reasons, shall we say.
Right. And being written in the 140s, this is a very early witness to how early Christians
understood that imagery that is found in the New Testament. Remember all your talks
about at the end of the first half. This is giving us a very early and authoritative way of
interpreting that imagery that we find in the New Testament. And if it's, hey, is the shepherd's
way of interpreting it or my way of interpreting it here in the 21st century more authoritative,
you kind of got to go with the shepherds on this one.
So that's sort of the the the the Protestant issues.
Um, the the the next big category of issues are scholarly issues.
So the first color we had in the second half kind of touched on this a little bit, uh, where
modern scholarship has attempted to derive points of systematic theology from the text
of the shepherd of Hermes and then critique them compared to later orthodox theological
formula.
It's just not that kind of text.
Yes, which in and of itself is weird.
Yeah.
Right.
And so one of the big examples of this is the Son of God in parable five.
I said we'd be coming back to this, right?
This is the vineyard, right?
And there's the tenant was identified as the Son of God.
So the Son of God in parable 5, it describes...
the pre-existent divine spirit, i.e. the Holy Spirit, who comes and indwells
this man, and that makes the man the Son of God by adoption.
Okay. And so most modern patristic scholars
till pretty recently have said, oh, this is summarizing the author.
view of Christology. Okay. This is saying, they claim, that Jesus was a man who was
adwelt by the Holy Spirit and made God by adoption. And therefore it has what
it would later be called an adoptionist Christology, which of course was later
declared heretical by the Orthodox Church.
So...
So this is one of these areas where we could point out some problems with modern scholars.
So first of all, even if that statement was about Christology, okay, and we're going to
question that in a minute.
But even if that is a statement about Christology, why would you think that was all of the authors
Christology?
Yeah, it's not a Christological treatise.
It's not a thing to set out.
here's for
theology about the people. He may have believed all kinds of other things. That could be a reference. If it what if it is Christology, let's say if it was Christology, that could be a reference to Christ's baptism when the Holy Spirit descended upon him and God said.
There you are my son today. I have forgotten the he could just be referencing Christ baptism. Yeah, yeah, and he could have a totally orthodox Christology.
And just it just so happens that in this one place in this one writing, he was referencing Christ's baptism.
Right?
So there's just this assumption, right?
There's just an assumption that this is about Christology and this is his whole Christology
summarized.
This one said imagery.
It's not even a statement.
It's like a parable.
It's imagery, right?
And we get derived his whole Christology from that.
That's a stupid assumption.
Frankly, right.
But then we have to question, is it even Christology?
Because wherever parable nine with the tower,
or it's being built on the ancient rock that is the Son of God,
how is that view of the Son of God compatible with the way scholars read parable five?
It's not right. And so this is where Father Bogdan comes in.
Father Bogdan, for all the kids, by the way, the present day, Father Bogdan,
at St. Vlad's, probably as we speak. Yeah, yeah. Right. And and this, this may be
wild for some of you guys who don't know this but like
Father Bogdan's work on the Shepherd of Hermas is so important in study of the
text of the Shepherd of Hermas. He's mentioned in the Wikipedia article about
the Shepherd of Hermas. Hey, because his work has kind of broken the scholarly
consensus about him. Nice. Because Father Bogdan pointed out a few things that
That'd make a lot of sense.
Number one.
Yeah, adoptionist Christology was condemned.
It was condemned very early.
Right?
Obviously, Nicaea rules it out completely.
Yeah.
325.
So, if the shepherd of hermists is teaching adoptionist Christology, why is St.
Athanasius recommending it for Catechuses?
Why are they still reading it in the fifth century?
authoritatively point father book Don right like there are early texts that teach
heretical Christology when the Christology gets condemned the text kind of go poof.
Yeah, you know five people still quoting them. Right. When origins started getting condemned,
you still had a lot of people cribbing from origin, but they stopped mentioning origin.
They didn't quote him. They just sort of plagiarized him. Subrosa, right?
So if it's clearly teaching this theoretical Christology, so that points to, positively, the
idea that there's got to be some other way that all of those very intelligent church
fathers were reading this text other than adoptionist Christology. And then Father Bogdan
goes on to make.
A very good guess at what that way of reading it was that makes actually more sense.
That the Son of God in Parable 5 is not Jesus.
It's you and me.
It's Christians who are sons of God by adoption because we've received the Holy Spirit.
See St. Paul.
I say it's such a good suggestion because it-
so obviously correct. Yeah, and very compatible with the
Athenages too. Like one thing a lot of people who just kind of quote what they think is a kind of slogan from on the incarnation.
You know God became man so that man might become divine might become God.
Have you want to translate it? Is that actually our my my late friend father Matthew Baker wrote a really good paper about this.
that theosis is very much connected with adoption by
over and over in his writings. So yeah, I mean, he's gonna look at this and would read it as
theoses. Yeah. Yeah. And it just makes sense. And that's in keeping with the themes of what
the other parables are about. Christian life, right? Yeah. You're about that. You're a person.
You're a human. You've received the Holy Spirit. You are a son of God by adoption. And now you
need to work in diligent.
in his vineyard. And if you do, you will receive a reward at the time of harvest at the judgment.
Yeah, I mean, I think this kind of underlines sometimes the way that we read these, when I say we,
I mean, you know, modern readers, read these texts is like, like, look at it as a whole, like,
why would he have this whole text about the right way to live the Christian life? And okay,
we're going to take a little Christology break here for a second, guys. And then go back
the whole Christian life repentance thing.
Yeah. Yeah. And so, uh,
relatedly there is what the, uh,
what the first caller in the last half brought up. And that is,
is the shepherd of Hermist teaching
binitarianism.
And you may be used to binitarianism being like
the father and the son, right? God the father and the logos and Christ, right? But
no, this would be, as the color intubated, this would actually be God and the
Holy Spirit and then Christ is sort of the son of God by virtue of this
adoption with the Holy Spirit and so the Holy Spirit and Christ are kind of
you know, mixed together, right? And you find this stuff about the Shepard Herbys in like
J&D Kelly's early Christian doctrines. Not J&D Kelly. Yeah. Yeah. It's been
quast as well. Say it's not quast. No, you want to, you've, you've got to remember, guys,
when you're reading secondary scholarly literature about this, especially from the late 19th and early
20th century. Best case it!
you're getting a high church Anglican.
Yeah, yeah.
Worst case scenario, you're getting a German.
Right, you're getting Vaughn Harnack instead of Kelly, right?
Oh, yeah.
That's the worst.
I pick out the Germans because, you know,
they picked on my homeland through the entire 20th century.
Tough, tough but fair.
I'm
And so why why are they doing this? Why are they getting this wrong? Why why are you
know and and they're all agreeing they're all how do you get this weird scholarly consensus
that father Bogdan has to come along and like be like duh right? No father Bogdan, I'm
not saying that all of your papers on this subject could be summarized as duh but you have
to stand with you very
mean, kind of refine accent that he has, you know, I don't think you are, I am really capable
of no, no, I can just do the California, duh. Um, right. And what is it? Well, it's a
presupposition with which you approach these texts. And it's one of the things I've been fighting
against, right? Like since religion of the Apostles, this developmental hypothesis, this
evolution
that all of these ideas, ideas of the church developed over time from a very low ecclesiology
to a very high ecclesiology.
Christology developed over time from a very low Christology to a very high Christology.
Yeah. New. Right. And so what they're doing.
And this is why even though it's the majority of modern scholarship until very recently,
the majority of modern scholarship until very recently.
I'm sorry, it's bad.
scholarship because they're reading the evidence through their theory rather than constructing
a theory based on the evidence.
Yeah.
Scholarship one of the kids.
They start with a theory and then the evidence, any evidence, newly discovered text, right?
Any evidence gets filtered through that theory.
So if the shepherd of Hermes is written in the one...
40s, it can't have a high Christology.
It can't have a nice in Christology because that had not, quote unquote, developed yet.
So it must have had a lowered Christology, like an adoptionist Christology.
Ah, here, look, if you read this sentence and you take it at a context, that sounds kind
like an adoptionist Christology that fits with our developmental paradigm.
There we go. We found more evidence for our theory.
Right? Horrible scholarship. That's horrible scholarship.
Right? What you are supposed to do is you're supposed to, when you do research, you're supposed to collect all of the available evidence.
And then you construct a theory by trying to find a theory that accurately explains and
describes...
and accounts for all of the evidence.
Another big place where you see this is, you will see them dating documents based on
how highly developed these things are.
You see this a lot with the books of the New Testament, right?
Say Paul can't have possibly written his pastoral epistles.
Why?
Well, they have a developed idea of leadership within the church.
That would have taken time to develop.
or it's based on the old covenant which had a very developed idea of leadership in the
people of God. That's reading the evidence through your pre-existing theory. Yeah. And
your pre-existing principle. Okay. So that's not how it's done. Okay. And so the reason we're
kind of having this again is I hope this is not just about the Shepard reverse. This is
when you're reading these things, when you're reading.
Secondary literature from scholars, you have to go to this level of cognition and ask these questions.
Right. Is that the only way to interpret that?
Is there a way of interpreting it, like I said to the caller, is there a way of interpreting it
where it would be orthodox, actually? If so, why are they, if there's other ways to read it,
why are they reading it the way they are?
Yeah.
And is it to fit some pre-existing theory of theirs?
Right?
And so it's important that you ask these questions that you don't just say, and especially, and
I've said this a bunch of times on the show, but always remember don't ever forget, right?
If someone says X is the scholarly consensus, that doesn't mean it's true, that means that's
That's what all the scholars are attacking right now.
right now and trying to disprove.
Right.
So there's a couple other weird things here as we conclude to point out.
So you will sometimes find the odd dispensationalist and they're all a little odd, but
who goes back to that great beast with the fiery locust breath at everything, you know.
Yeah!
cool. He wanted to try to read this is, oh, this is an early source for the teaching of the
rapture. Wait, what? It's those four colors, right? Oh, and the fact that it uses the phrase
the great tribulation. Oh, I mean, that's a dead giveaway. We're talking distant thunder
stuff right? Right. Yeah.
And so therefore see the gold, the people who are spared the great tribulation, they get raptured.
Right? Wow.
Now first of all, it's very clear in the text, if you actually read it in context,
that the gold is the people who have been refined by passing through the fire and the blood.
They have been purified by the great tribulation.
Or as Christ said, that He's praying not that God would take the
out of the world, but that he has, he's from the devil. Now before you post-trib rapture,
people get all excited though. Right? It is also not that. Why? Well, because the way
Daniel actually talks about the great tribulation and uses that language, it's referring to the
persecution that came under this cell, you kids, hmm, like the abomination of desolation,
Right, and Tychus Epiphanies.
All of that persecution.
Right? And so, just as St. John does in the book of Revelation with no S at the end people,
at the book of Revelation, so also is the shepherd of Hermes using the great tribulation to
refer to Roman persecution. Okay? And so, just as he sees, as we've seen in the text,
Context, context is there...
everything. As we've seen in the text, just as he sees the hardships of this life, the material hardships of this life, as bringing about repentance and purification from sin, he sees the persecution directed at Christians as being purifying.
Hmm, when you endure it patiently, so that's what he's talking about.
Okay.
Um, and then the last...
That's weird thing is another scholarly thing.
Okay.
This is, this is, and this one is especially funny to me because it's so weird, right?
And I check some things out with this.
So just about anywhere you look about the shepherd of Hermes, right?
From Wikipedia and AI at these low goofy end all the way up to J&D Kelly and scholars
read out scholars always have this line about how the shepherd of
Herbys is clearly from a group of Jewish Christians who still kept parts of
the law of Moses. Oh no, they all say this. They all say this. And this is weird to
me. So I did some investigating. The phrase law of Moses and anything about
Moses. Never appears at the text.
right. They refer to the law of Moses, all of these scholars and all of these sources,
but law of Moses never appears to the text. Okay. So I've minded it in there. Emphasis on
doing stuff. Is that the right? No, it's the word commandments. Oh, you kidding me.
And the phrase the laws of God. Wow. I mean, I seem to remember a certain someone saying
if you love me you'll keep my commandments.
Yes, but that's literally it.
They're like, it has to be Jewish,
because they're keeping part of the law of Moses.
They're interpreting commandments as part of the law of Moses.
Okay, but even if they are, wow, okay,
unless you're a Marcianite
and we've seen this text maybe actually condemning Marcian,
right, unless you're a Marcianite,
as a Christian, you keep part of the law of Moses.
Like the apostles told you to.
There are no Christians who believe
the law of Moses was completely abolished.
none of the Commandments still apply. Yeah. Gentile Christians were not all
Marcy-Enyts, they were not Antonovians.
So it makes no sense, right? But it's been high-lined it. I think everybody's just
quoting each other now. I mean that's how the Internet works. Yes, in this weird
recursive loop. Yeah, right? It just sort of sounds right I guess. I don't know.
This is what
This guy said it.
Like bizarre.
So this is, you know, there's got to ask questions
when you read this stuff folks.
Yeah.
You got to ask questions of the text,
these secondary texts.
Okay.
You know, about,
when you read something about the shepherd of Hermes, right?
Do not assume that anything it's saying
is necessarily correct.
Right.
Ask questions, right?
Wait, why is that right?
Like, I know everything says that,
but I don't see that in the text, right?
Never mentioned Moses.
Yeah.
And again, what is it reveal?
Well, reveal some kind of weird presuppositions
of the probably, in this case,
Protestant scholar who first came up with it, right?
Oh, commandments?
Oh no, yeah, Christianity isn't about commandment keeping.
This must be some...
like Jewish Christians. Why would you think Christianity isn't about commandment keeping?
Even Luther and Calvin would have told you that read Luther's Taticism, right?
Yeah. Structuring around the ten commandments as a guide to the Christian life, like what?
But there you have it. Ask questions, people. Question everything.
So I have a number of takeaways that I could comment on in this episode.
But the thing that occurs to me, especially here at the end, is I don't know if we've ever
discussed this on the show, but you and I have discussed in the past because sometimes
we like to read, frankly, as a form of entertainment.
We like to read the reviews of the books we've read, but other people's...
books as well, but you know, you can't help but look at the reviews of your own books.
And one of the themes that we've, that you've pointed out, and I've noticed this as well,
is that many of the reviews could be boiled down to, I agreed with this book. I did not
agree with this book. And that the whole point of reading the book was apparently to see
if you agreed with it or not, which is a waste of time in most...
I'm sure there's some context in which would I be a waste of time.
But it's just a waste of time.
And the reason why it's a waste of time is because if you come to a book or any text and
the question you're asking is does this measure up to what I already think?
then you are the measure of all things.
And you didn't read to learn some...
I mean, I'm not saying that every book you read is going to be correct, obviously not.
Obviously not.
But if the point of reading a book is just to see whether or not you agree with it,
then you're basically what you're doing is you're trying, you're giving it a grade.
You're the teacher.
You're not the student.
Student doesn't have to agree with everything and teacher says, but a student doesn't need
to come in with curiosity.
Rather...
than the posture of judgment.
And why do I mention all this?
Well, I think not just because of all the stuff
that you just went through, Father,
about how a lot of scholars come to these texts
and have all these presuppositions
that they're bringing to the text.
Again, basically making it pointless to even read
because they came in deciding
what they were gonna see to begin with.
So that's one part of it.
But also, I think that especially looking at a text like this, you know, these second
century Christian texts, particularly with the way that most of us in the West, whether
we are raised as Protestants or not, we have these assumptions about what texts are
for
But it's not just our 19th century German friends that give us these assumptions.
There's something actually much more recent than that, which is I think the fact that so
many of us, and I hold myself included in this, I mean, I have this problem, everybody,
I think almost everybody has this problem now.
our attention spans and the focus of our attention, the intensity of our attention.
has been so truncated by social media addiction, but it's not just social media.
It's also the kind of sound bite world that we live in, that the, you know, TLDR, right,
too long didn't read, that that gets applied now to texts that are only like a thousand words
long. This is too long. I can't read something like that.
or even a few paragraphs long. It's just too long. I can't read something like that.
And so as a result, we're looking for sound bites and if something presents some kind of
challenge to us, then what we're looking for when we approach it is not, what can I learn from this,
but rather, how can I either accept or dismiss this right away?
Right? And I think this is why a lot of people look at writings of the yearly church in this way.
And especially one like the Shepherd of Hermas, which...
You can see him a little odd if you're not used to this kind of text.
Right?
And even people say things like this is dangerous to read.
Dangerous.
You might get some of the wrong ideas.
Okay.
The likelihood of that happening, I think, unless someone is extremely self-willed and...
You know often I've even heard that I do
heard this expressed in that way in Orthodox contexts. But I think that most people, frankly,
who pick up a copy of the Apostolic Fathers, even if they're new to the Orthodox faith,
which honestly when I read these texts the first time, I was new. Almost 30 years ago,
now I was new. I was just looking at my old copy this afternoon, as I mentioned, and
I looked in the front, I'd read my name in the front, and there was no title in front
of my name I didn't put any
abbreviation. Meaning I was a layman when I bought that book and read it. Most people are not picking
up a book like that and going, how can I enslave myself to these words? Right? So I think there's
not much that's dangerous about reading something like this. Now, what can be dangerous is if you are
functioning in an isolated way and you're functioning a self-willed way and you're not part of the church
and you're not listening to your father confess.
answer, then yeah, it could be dangerous. But if that's the way that you're approaching
Christian life, your problem is not that you picked up a copy of the Apostolic Fathers.
You have a much bigger problem, which is that you have no sense of obedience or of being
part of a community, right? And in our sound bite, short attention span, TLDR, let me
just figure out whether I agree with this.
or not, way of approaching the world, what we are doing is condemning ourselves, if
we continue to live that way, we are condemning ourselves to a very deep form of loneliness
and isolation.
We make snap decisions and judgments about everything.
And every one, I like this one, I don't like this one.
This one's canceled.
This one's my people.
whatever it might be.
And so I think that one of the great values of reading a text like the Shepherd of Hermos is that we can enter into it
Frankly, even if you haven't listened to a three plus hour episode of Laura Spirits podcast talking about it.
And we've only really in some ways just scratched the surface of the things could be said about this.
Is it okay to enter into some of these things with a sense of unknowing, of wonder, of wonder
You know, oh, I wonder what's in here. Let's go explore. Let's go find it out. Let's
Become a little bit bigger than we were. You know, um,
I think it's okay
to encounter something that is
weird to us
and to be changed by the experience. I don't find that dangerous, especially if we're
As I said, within the context of the church community
living the life of the church. If that is the case, if you're doing that, then this stuff cannot hurt you.
But I think the real reason that people feel like it's dangerous is they want to either dismiss
or approve of something. And like, let's just move beyond that. You know, I've got stuff to do.
But at some point, if you do that and you just keep doing that, you're going to get to the end of your
life saying, well, I certainly made a bunch of judgments. But did I learn anything? Did I get anywhere?
Did I change? Did I struggle? Did I ask any questions and actually look for the answers and not walk in thinking I have them all already?
So I think that encountering some of these things is a great boon to our humility and our obedience.
Maybe you read a text like this, you walk away going, I couldn't make heads or tails of that.
And that's okay.
That's okay.
It's good to have that experience sometimes just to take the journey.
And even if at the end you say, I don't know what that was about.
That's okay.
That's all right.
The Bible is that way too.
I think if there's anything that people would walk away from listening to this show, it's
that the Bible is a deeply weird book.
And that's part of what gives it its power as that we encounter.
something strange, something that provokes us and wakes us up and calls us out of our self-containedness,
so that we can actually encounter something other than ourselves and someone other than ourselves.
Because we're not the gods of this world, we are not the measure of all things. We're just people,
but were people that Christ.
came to this earth and suffered and died and herald Hades and rose from the dead
four. And in the words of the great Yankee poet that has made all the
difference. So that's why I have to say about that.
So, one of the reasons I'm always telling people while poning noobs.
in Marvel rivals that they should read more St. John Cachean.
Is that a lot of his work is in the same vein as I mentioned earlier as the
Shepard of Hermes.
And so much of patristic literature and Christian literature from most of Christian
history, in terms of living a Christian life,
striving to acquire virtues, striving.
to avoid sin and repent of sin and pursue following Christ.
And that kind of literature, even though it's most of Christian literature, even though
it's at the heart of what Christianity has historically been, it is somehow through
the machinations of modern evangelicalism and devalued forms of Protestantism that exist
in the 21st century become kind of
of weirdly counterintuitive because so much of, you know, and again, I know the America
best, so much of American Christianity has become about like, okay, what are the things I
need to do so I can just relax and I'm okay. Like me and God are okay. Like, what do I have
to do? And as at least some of you know, I've been involved in some discussions online.
about salvation outside the Orthodox Church and the Orthodox view.
And I think sometimes in those discussions that like
despite not being what I'm trying to say, what
the other person is hearing is something like,
so you're saying in addition to whatever you have to do to be
some kind of Christian in general, you also have to join the Orthodox Church in order to go to heaven.
Right. Is if I'm adding like one more box you have to
check, right? You have to be, you know, because the questions I'm getting are like, are what's
bringing that out. And this was really sort of brought home to me when I saw an interaction
between a pretty prominent Protestant leader who was told by
someone who was formerly affiliated in a certain way with their ministry that they had become Orthodox,
that they had joined the Orthodox Church there now in Orthodox Christian. And the Protestant leader
asked, why would you give up resting in the perfect righteousness of Christ?
because that was sort of the whole orientation of his theory.
was toward, it's done, you're good. You can rest now. You can have this kind of assurance, you don't have to worry.
And it really struck me how foreign that idea of resting in anything was to how the Scriptures, the Bible, talk about the Christian life.
Life.
Say
Paul talking about pressing on toward the prize, pressing on so that he having preached
to others isn't himself excluded.
Right, compared to running a race to fighting a battle, this ongoing thing, talking about
striving to come to maturity, to become perfect, to bring things to completion, right, to
have the fullness of the stature of Christ formed in you.
of that sounds like
and something that's already done the day after you're saved.
None of that sounds like being comfortable and self-assured.
And literature like the shepherd of Hermes and like St. John Cacin's writings,
and I just happen to be some of my favorites, but all of this other volumes upon volumes of...
Christian literature throughout the history of the church all sounds a lot more like scripture to me.
And it's really practical and brass tax about what it means to follow Christ and seek
virtue and bear fruit in Christ and strive to completion and for our reward on the day
of judgment.
And so I think this literature is important.
like the shepherd of Hermas are important, especially for us.
especially for the people listening to this right now in our present age.
Because the fact that it seems weird and that that approach seems counterattuitive
means we need to reprogram ourselves a little.
We've been a little over-programmed by our religious culture that isn't
fully Christian in the full-bodied historical sense of the word Christianity.
Shall we say?
There's we are.
seek to pick up our cross and follow Christ and we all seek to complete the race and strive
for perfection, and we urge each other on to do so, and we help each other in community
to do so. We need literature like this to help us understand how, to help us understand
and find and seek out in the sins that we need to repent of, to know how it is that we can
and develop certain virtues that we struggle with like patients.
or joy in some cases, or loving the unlovable.
So I hope that as we said earlier that this sort of you take this episode not as a substitute
for reading the Shepard of Hermes but as an orientation to help you profitably read the Shepard of
Hermes and other similar literature. Yeah. And that's true with all the the sort of literature review
episodes we do.
because these texts have a lot to communicate to us and to teach us in a lot of ways to help sort of reshape us
into the Christians that were called to be.
Cool. Cool.
Well, don't forget everybody. We've got a couple of pre-recorded episodes coming to you in July, which most of you will not have heard that information.
but we'll be back live again in August but that is our show for today.
Thank you everyone for listening.
If you did not happen to get through to us live this time around, we'd like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsNationFate.com.
You can send us a message on our Facebook page.
You can leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity,
or you need help to find a parish, go to Orthodoxintro.org.
Enjoy this for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 6 p.m. Eastern 3 p.m. Pacific.
I've ruled out an intelligence
But it might be a super intelligent virus and it's playing with me.
And if you are on Facebook, you can follow our page, you can join our big discussion group.
And give us a rating, thumbs up, click, click, subscribe, subscribe, and most importantly,
share this show with one of your friends.
And finally be sure to go to www.inxuffaith.com.store to support it and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
I'm Commander Shepard, and this is my favorite store on the Citadel.
Thank you.
night, and make up as you always.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported
presentation of Ancient Faith Radio. And I be held, and I heard the voice of many
angels round about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders, and the number of
them was 10,000 times 10,000, then thousands of thousands.
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.